- Hi everybody. In this lesson,
I'm finally gonna start
simulating random variables.
And again, this by way of doing
some review of prob and stats,
but I figured I'd sneak
in some simulation now.
Here's the lesson overview.
Last time we started
our probability primer.
All right, finally.
And this time, I'm gonna
show you how to simulate
some very easy random
variables on the computer.
And of course, this is
one of the main reasons
that you're taking this class.
So first of all, let's start out
with kind of the easiest example.
I'm just gonna pick a random integer,
a discrete uniform
distribution from one to n.
In other words, the
random variable X equals i
with probability one over n
for i equals one, two, up to n.
This is like a n-sided
dice toss or die toss
for Dungeons and Dragons people.
So, here's how we do it.
If U is a uniform zero
one random variable,
which I can get in Excel
using the RAND function.
We'll talk more about uniform
zero ones in a little while.
We can simulate a discrete
uniform random variate,
simply by setting X equal to
n times a number between zero and one,
random number between zero and one,
and then rounding up,
taking the ceiling function.
It's very, very easy, and you'll see why.
For example, let's take n equals 10,
so we have a ten-sided die toss.
I'm going to sample a uniform
number between zero and one.
Let's pretend it turns out to be 0.73
the number between zero and one.
Then, that gives me X equal
to the ceiling function
of n times U, ceiling function of 7.3,
and that equals eight. So very simple.
I get a uniform of 0.73 and that gives me
a discrete uniform of
eight. Very, very easy.
Here's another discrete random variable.
This one's a little more complicated.
Let's let little f of x
or the probability that f equals little x
equal to 0.25, if x equals minus two,
0.10 if x equals three,
and 0.65 if x equals 4.2.
And notice how those things add up to one.
Now, I can't use a die
toss to simulate this one.
This is a little bit too complicated.
So I'm going to use what's sort of called
the inverse transform method.
Here's what it is.
We'll go into more
detail on this later on,
but I make a little table.
x, little f of x, the cdf, capital F of x,
or probably that x is less
than or equal to little x,
and then associated uniform zero one.
So what I mean by that,
the x values are minus
two, three, and 4.2.
I just make those up. Little f of x,
read the previous
definition of probability
that X equals little x.
That's 0.25, 0.10, 0.65 respectively.
The cdf at those points,
well I just add up the pmfs.
0.25, 0.35, 1.00. That's the third column.
Now, let's associate some
uniforms with those cdf values.
The first value of x, x equals minus two,
that corresponds to a cdf of 0.25.
So any time I sample a
uniform between zero and 0.25,
that's going to correspond
to x equals minus two.
x equals three has a probability of 0.10,
and the cdf at that point is 0.35.
I'm going to correspond to
that x equals three value,
the uniforms 0.25 to 0.35.
The probability that I end
up with a uniform between
0.25 and 0.35 is 0.10,
just the probability that
I want for x equals three.
And the final value, x equals 4.2,
that is the probability of 0.65,
all correspond uniforms to
be between 0.35 and 1.0,
thus completing the whole
grid of uniform zero ones
and let's see what we get here.
Let's sample a uniform and we choose
the corresponding x value, in other words,
we take the inverse, x
equals F inverse of U.
Don't worry about that for now,
because we'll talk about it later.
For example, if U equals 0.46,
you look at that third line,
that falls between 0.35 and 1.00,
so that corresponds to x equals 4.2.
Much more on this later.
Now, I'm going to use inverse transform
to generate continuous random variable.
Here's the main result.
We'll prove it later on.
Theorem: If X is a
continuous random variables
with cdf capital F of x,
then the random variable capital
F of capital X is uniform.
Now this is crazy. What the
thing on the second line there,
capital F of capital X,
that is not a cdf anymore,
because there's a capital X sitting there
in the middle of that, not a little x.
It's capital F of capital X.
That thing is a nasty,
horrible random variable.
Okay, fine. What that's
gonna allow me to do though,
just take my word for it for now,
since that's uniform,
according to my theorem,
which I haven't proven for you,
I'm going to just set
capital F of capital X
equal to the uniform and
solve backwards for x.
So that's going to require that I can take
X equals to F inverse of
U. That's the inverse cdf.
And so what I'll be able to do,
if I can solve for X, that
generates a value of X,
given that I can come up with a uniform,
which I can from Excel or from
any other programing language.
Here's an example, suppose capital X
random variable is exponential,
then the cdf of the
exponential is a real function,
capital F of little x is one
minus e to the minus lambda x
for X greater than zero.
We showed you that before.
So now if I plug in capital X to get this
big, horrible, nasty random variable,
one minus e to the minus lambda capital X,
that gives me a uniform distribution
according to the theorem.
That is a messy, awful random variable.
I set it equal to U and solve for X.
Here's what I get after
a little bit of algebra,
which we'll go through later.
X equals negative one over lambda
natural log of one minus U.
That's exponential. Amazing.
So if I take a uniform,
plug it into that thing,
I get an exponential. Beautiful.
Now the only things I
haven't told you about is
how do you generate uniforms?
Well the above random
number generation examples,
they all required us to
generate basically independent
and identically distributed uniforms.
I'm going to use iid from now on,
because it's a mouth
full. How do you do that?
If I'm lazy I can just go to
Excel and use the RAND function
or something similar,
your favorite language,
but what I'm going to do is
I'll give you an algorithm
to generate these
pseudo random numbers,
which we talked about
in the tour of simulation.
What it's gonna do, it's
gonna give me a series,
we'll call them R one,
R two, dot, dot, dot
of deterministic numbers that
appear to be iid uniform.
So these are not really random numbers,
but to you and me they're gonna look it.
And there are deterministic
algorithms to do this.
I need to start out with a seed,
an integer seed just to get going.
Let's pick your favorite
fairly large integer, x naught,
and you calculate X i equal to 16807
the previous integer, X i minus one
mod two to the 31st minus one.
Now we had gone over this in the tour,
we'll give more details in this later on.
So the first one, x one is gonna
equal 16807 times x naught,
which you've already picked out.
Mod two to the 31st minus one.
The second one, x two
equals 16807 times x one,
which you just calculated,
mod two to the 31st minus one.
This is gonna give me a
series of very large integers.
X one, x two, dot, dot, dot.
I'm going to turn them into my
supposedly pseudo random numbers,
R i by just taking my
integers and dividing
by the biggest possible integer
from my modular arithmetic
two to the 31st minus one.
This is little bit of a
hassle to program by yourself,
but it's really kinda
easy. It's not that bad.
You can program it by yourself,
you can use the following pseudo code.
Here's a FORTRAN
implementation for instance,
from an old book by
Bratley, Fox, and Schrage.
I won't go through the details
here, we'll do that later,
but it's basically two or
three lines of code here.
And it works really well,
so you can look at this
yourself during the commercials
while you're watching
you favorite TV show.
This thing actually works pretty well.
And it gives me proper uniforms.
So what you do, you input your
favorite x naught integer,
and the functions returns a
pseudo random number called UNIF
as well as an updated integer
that you can go and use again.
And this thing works pretty well.
A couple exercises I'm gonna
just blow through these.
Look at them at your leisure.
These are sort of bonus exercises.
You can use whatever you
want, these are bonus.
As long as you can give me a uniform,
you can do these very easily.
Make a histogram of minus
natural log of U one.
It turns out, of U sub i.
These are gonna give you
exponential random variables.
You can try that by yourself.
Now you can plug in to a slightly
more complicated function.
Let's generate X i and Y i.
Those are going to be
independent pairs of uniforms.
Plug into this nasty
equation for Z i equals
square root of minus two log
of X i times sin of two pi Y i.
See what you get.
I think you're gonna feel pretty
normal about what you get.
And finally this really nasty one.
Again, let X i and Y i
be independent uniforms.
Now define Z i as X i over X i minus Y i.
I'm not gonna tell you what you get,
but it's something very interesting.
So what you do, you
plug in the X i and Y i.
Do that ten thousand
times. Make a histogram.
See what you get and it's
gonna be something interesting.
Here's summary of this lesson.
This was actually a starter lesson
on random variate generation.
Just get psyched up.
Good stuff is coming up.
And next time I know that
you've been expecting this,
but we're gonna have a nice
lecture on expectations!
So, I'll see you then.
(ethereal music)