- Hi everyone.
So now we're finally
gonna start our review
on some Probability basics, and again,
if you've had these for
requisites that's just great,
if not, have some fun and sort of recall
maybe what you might've seen
for the first time way back
even in high school if you
took an AP Stats class.
So here's the lesson overview.
In the previous lesson we
completed our Calculus Primer,
did a little bit of numerical integration.
This time I'm gonna start
a review of Probability
with some very easy basics,
and if you're a tyro,
which means beginner,
feel free to peruse, take a look at,
the notes at your leisure,
but you know, pay
attention to the material
that you don't happen to remember so well.
So here are the basics.
I'm gonna assume that you know
about the real, real basics
like sample spaces, events,
and even the definition of probability,
so if somebody tells you
well I think that this thing happens
with a probability greater than one
or a probability less than zero,
you'll laugh at them because we know
that probabilities can only
be between zero and one.
So I'm assuming you know stuff like that.
Anyway, here's sort of a definition
I always start out with in such a class,
and that is the definition
of conditional probability.
So the probability of some event A,
given event B, is equal to the probability
of the intersection of
the two events A and B
divided by the probability
of B all by itself.
That's called the conditional
probability of A given B.
And this assumes that the probability of B
is greater than zero so you don't
run into these dividing
by zero type issues
but this is a very standard definition.
Now, if you don't like math,
just think of it as the probability
that A is going to occur
given the updated information B,
and we'll do a couple
examples to show you.
This is certainly something
that we'll be using throughout the course.
So, what's the probability
that an event A happens
given that your friend has
told you that B has happened?
And this allows you to
update the probabilities.
Now for instance, what's the probability
that it's gonna rain today
given that it's rained
for the last four days?
That's probably not
equal to the probability
it's gonna rain today, given
no information whatsoever.
Let's go through an example or two
and we can expand on this.
Let's toss a fair die.
I'm gonna define the event A
as having a one, two, or a three appear
and I'll define the event B
as having a three, four,
five, or six appear.
Then the probability of A given B
which means what's the
probability that I saw
a one or a two or a three
given that my friend secretly told me,
well, a three, four,
five, or six appeared,
but I'm not gonna tell you which one.
So what's the probability that
a one, two, three appeared
given that my friend has
already told me that,
well, a three, four,
five, or six has appeared?
Well, what's gonna happen here
is that my friend has eliminated
the possibility of one and two,
so the probability of A
intersect B in this case
is just the probability
that a three occurred,
which equals 1/6.
The probability of B all
by itself occurring is 4/6
and so even my cat can do this division.
1/6 over 4/6, the updated
probability of A occurring is 1/4.
So before we did the experiment
the probability of A
occurring all by itself,
the probability of getting
a one, two, or three,
that was 1/2.
But given that my friend has
told me this information,
that a three, four, five,
or six has occurred,
the updated probability of A occurring
unfortunately goes down to 1/4,
so there's lots of interesting problems
that you can do.
On the homework I'll give you
one or two that you can enjoy.
Here's another definition.
If the probability of A intersect B
equals P of A times P of B,
then A and B are called
independent events,
and I'll give some motivation for that.
For instance, if I'm interested
in looking at the temperature on Mars
and the IBM stock price,
it turns out that those are
gonna be independent events,
they have nothing to do with each other,
and I'll show you where this
nothing to do with each other
motivation comes from in a second.
So, at least they would have you believe
that they have nothing
to do with each other.
Hopefully they are in fact independent.
Theorem, this is sort of the motivational
definition of independence.
If A and B are independent,
then the probability of A given B
equals the probability of A all by itself,
so this is not a
definition, it's a theorem,
and it's kind of a nice theorem
that I sort of pretend is a definition.
What it means is the information
that my friend gives me about B
does not affect the
probability of A at all,
so the probability of A
occurring given that I know B,
that's just the probability
of A all by itself.
B has given no influence on
the probability of A occurring,
so that's why they're called independent,
B has nothin' to do with A.
Here's an example, let's toss two dice.
I'll let A equal the event
that the sum is a seven,
and B is gonna be the event
that the first die is a four.
A die is the singular version of dice,
I'm not being gross here.
So the probability of A is 1/6
because there are six ways
that you can get a seven.
You can get a one and a six,
you can get a two and a five, dot dot dot.
There's six ways you can do it,
six out of 36, and so that translates
to a probability of 1/6.
The probability of B occurring,
that the first die is a four,
well let's just look at the first die.
One, two, three, four, five, six,
one of those possibilities
is first die is a four,
so that probability is also 1/6,
Okay, meanwhile the
probability of A intersect B,
the only way that A can intersect B
if the sum is a seven and
the first die is a four,
that must be that the first die is a four
and the second die is a three,
that must be, it's the
only way to intersect,
and so that event, a four and a three,
has a probability of
1/36, which by coincidence
is probability of A
times probability of B,
1/6 times 1/6, and so it shows
that the two events in that case, A and B,
are independent of each
other, congratulations.
Let's jump over to the
definition of a random variable.
Don't be frightened by this
'cause there's a little
equation, it's nothing at all.
Random variable's just a function X
from the sample space of the experiment
to the real line.
I'll give an example to
show what I mean by that.
Let X be the sum of two dice rolls.
So the sample space is all the
pairs of possible dice rolls.
One one, one two, dot dot
dot, all the way to six six.
What's that called, boxcars I guess?
So in particular, one set of tosses
could be a four and a six,
and that adds up to 10.
So what happens, my
function X takes an element
of the sample space, four six,
and it moves it over to the real line.
So four six gets transformed
over to the real line.
In addition, the probability that x equals
any particular specific value,
so capital X is the random thing,
little x is a specific value.
We know that the probability of the sum
of two dice tosses is,
if the sum is two the probability is 1/36,
there's only one way you can do it,
get a one and a one.
To get little x equal to
three, the sum equals three,
the only ways you can do that
are tossing a one and a two
or a two and a one, so that's 2/36.
And so you can see you get this,
what's called a probability mass function.
1/36, 2/36, it goes all the way up
to 6/36 when x equals seven,
then it comes back down
to 1/36 for x equals 12.
That brings to mind a general
class of random variables,
or I call 'em recreational
variables sometimes.
So the definition I'm aiming at here is,
if the number of possible values,
of our random variable X,
is finite or countably infinite,
and in that last example it was finite,
there were 12, there were 11
values, x equals two to 12.
Then X is called a
discrete random variable.
Its probability mass function, or pmf,
is given by little f of x,
that's a function of
x, and it's defined as
the probability that X equals any of these
finite or countably infinite x values,
and note that they add up to
one, all these probabilities.
The sum of x over little
f of x equals one.
By countably infinite I mean
there could be an infinite
number of these things,
but they have a one to one
correspondence with the integers,
that's what countably infinite means.
Example, let's flip two coins,
X is the number of heads.
X can only equal zero, one, or two,
so the probability that
I flip the two coins
and get zero heads is 1/4,
the probability that I
get two heads, also 1/4.
And the probability that
I get exactly one head,
so I either get heads
tails or tails heads,
that's equal to 1/2.
And there's no other
possible values for X.
1.5, not possible, negative
three, not possible.
So if you add up all those numbers,
1/4 plus 1/4 plus 1/2,
wow, magic, it's equal to one.
And we have a bunch of other
discrete random variables you may remember
from Baby Stats class,
Bernoulli random variable,
Binomial, Geometric, Poissin,
I'll talk about all those as we need them,
so don't panic if you don't remember.
Now, the other class of random variables
that we're interested in
are what's called
continuous random variables.
A continues random variable is one
that has probability zero
at every individual point,
and in this case there exists
what's called a probability
density function, or pdf.
F of x having the magical property
that, well, f of x is not a probability
like it was for the
probability mass function,
but you can get
probabilities from the pdf.
And namely, here's how you do it.
If A is any set or any event,
then the probability
that X falls in that set
is merely the integral of
f of x taken over that set,
and so f of x, the pdf
is not a probability,
but it gets you the probabilities.
People mess that up all the time,
but that's what it is,
and note that if I integrate f of x
over the entire real line,
that integrates to one.
That's kinda like adding up
the pmf and getting a one.
So here's the simplest
example I could think of.
Just pick a random real number
between three and seven.
There are an infinite number
of real numbers between three and seven,
and in fact, it's uncountably infinite,
which is a bigger infinity
than countably infinite,
believe it or not.
So, the probability that I pick
any individual value
between three and seven,
like suppose, what's a
probability that I pick a five,
that probability is zero,
'cause I could have easily
picked 5.00001 or 4.99999
so the probability of any
individual number is zero,
that kinda corresponds to the integral
of a continuous function over one point.
So, even though f of x is not
the probability of the event,
it's the pdf, which gives me the ability
to calculate probabilities,
and for purposes of this,
what's called uniform distribution
between three and seven,
the pdf is equal to 1/4 for
x between three and seven,
and notice if you integrate
1/4 from three to seven
that gives you a one, so
things kinda make sense.
Now, some famous continuous
random variables,
which you've heard of, are Uniform,
Exponential, and Normal, or Gaussian,
we'll talk more about those later.
For now, I'm very, very lazy,
I'm gonna use that little twiddle thing,
that means is distributed as.
I don't like writin'
things out, save some ink.
So if I write x twiddle Uniform 0.1,
that means that X has
the uniform distribution
from zero to one.
Now, I'll give one more definition
for any random variable, x
either discrete or continuous,
the cumulative distribution
function, or cdf,
is the probability of
everything that's happened
up to little x.
So capital F of x is the probability
that capital X is less than or equal
to the particular value little x.
Capital X is random, little
x is a specific value,
and the thing on the right-hand side
is basically the integral
from minus infinity
to x of little f of y dy,
so everything that's
happened up to time x,
that's if X is continuous.
The reason I'm using little y,
is it's just a dummy variable,
and it's the same thing with the summation
effects as a discrete random variable.
Notice that capital F of x,
when you let x go to
minus infinity it's zero,
because the probability of x
being less than minus infinity is zero.
Similarly, the probability that X
is less than infinity is one,
and the nice thing is, if X is continuous
you take the derivative of
big X, you get little f.
Uh, take the derivative of
big F, you get little f,
and vice versa, integrate
little f, you get big F,
that's by fundamental theorem of Calculus.
Example, flip two coins.
Number of heads?
Well remember the probability
that we would get zero heads is 1/4,
so nothing happens until
you get x equal to zero,
that's why there's a
zero on the first line
and 1/4 on the second line.
Then nothing happens
until you get to x equals one,
whereupon the probability
that x equals one is 1/2
so the cumulative probability goes from
1/4 plus 1/2 to 3/4,
and then nothing happens
until you get to x equals two,
whereupon the cdf jumps up to one
because 3/4 plus the
probability that x equals two,
which is 1/4, that equals one.
In the continuous case, let's pretend
x has the exponential lambda distribution.
This is the old friend
that I reminded you about
a slide or so ago, that just means
that little f of x is
lambda elim minus lambda x,
that is by definition,
and that's for x greater than zero.
Well, if you integrate
that thing from zero to x,
because you don't need to worry
about anything below x equals zero,
if you integrate that from zero to x
it turns out with elementary Calculus
that capital F of x is equal to one
minus elim minus lambda x.
We'll go through this again
in more detail later on
'cause it's a very important distribution.
Here's the summary.
We started out our basic
review of Probability
and next time I'm gonna show ya
how to do some simulation
in random variables,
it's about time, huh?
So we will see you then.