- In this lesson, we're
gonna be continuing
our probability boot camp,
except I might diverge a little
into classic literature.
In this lesson, we'll be
doing Great Expectations.
So, here's the lesson overview.
Last time, I took a brief detour
to show you how to simulate
some very easy random variables.
In this lesson, I'll be back to the
formal Probability Review.
In particular, this module
is gonna be all about
taking expected values
of random variables.
Now, we'll be paying particular attention
to something called LOTUS,
L-O-T-U-S, and we'll talk about that soon.
So, the fundamental definition
that we'll be working with
is the expected value,
or mean, of a random variable X.
That's defined as
E of X equals, and now what I've done
is I've broken things up into two pieces,
a discrete version and
a continuous version.
So, this discrete version
is just summation over all values of X
of X times f of X,
and that's if X is a
discrete random variable,
and every place we see a summation,
we put an integral sign
if X is continuous.
So, the expected value
of X is the integral
over all X, of X times f of X DX.
In either case, the
expected value is basically
just a weighted average of the X values,
and the weights are the f of X's,
the probability mass, or
probability density functions.
Now, if you're real into notation,
here's a shorthand,
and occasionally, I'll use this
integral, or the real line of
X times d f of X.
D, f of X, d capital f of X,
is just shorthand notation for
the two braced items to the left.
Here's an example, very simple example
for the Bernoulli distribution,
so X has the Bernoulli p distribution,
if X equals one with probability p and
X equals zero with probability one minus,
which sometimes they'll call that q.
So that's just a coin
flip with probability, p,
of landing on heads, or X
equals one in that case.
Probability q of landing
on tails, X equals zero.
So here, we have the expected value of X,
just the summation overall
X of X times f of X,
that's a discrete random variable,
and you can see right here,
it's just a X can take
the value of zero and one,
so it's zero times f of zero
plus one times f of one.
F of one equals p, and so
it simplifies down to p,
as we have, on the bottom there.
So that's the expected value
of a Bernoulli random variable.
Here's another example, this
is the continuous example.
X is a Uniform distribution from a to b,
and what that means is
that X is sample uniformly
sort of with equal probability,
anywhere between a and b.
In this case, f of X
equals one over b minus a,
for all values of X between a and b.
And you can see that that's
just the equal sampling,
sort of, between a and b.
So this is a continuous random variable.
And so for the expected value,
we now take the integral,
over all values, X, between a and b.
So the integral of X
time f of X from a to b,
after the smoke clears,
it's just a plus b over two.
And in fact, if you draw
a picture out of f of X,
it's just a constant, one over b minus a,
you can see that the average
is just that a plus b over two.
You can tell just by looking at the thing.
Let's look at a slightly more
difficult continuous example,
namely, let's supposed
that X is distributed
as an Exponential distribution
with parameter lambda.
In this case, f of X just equals lambda e
to the minus lambda X
for X greater than zero,
and zero otherwise,
and this often represents the distribution
of the lifetime of say a light bulb,
or some electrical component.
In any case, the expected value of X,
we're gonna have to do
some integration by parts,
and the L'Hospital's Rule,
and all sorts of stuff,
I'll let you go through that.
The expected value of X,
since it's continuous,
is gonna be the integral from
X equals zero to infinity
of X times f of X, as we're
starting at zero in this case,
X times f of X is X times
lambda e to the minus lambda X,
after the smoke clears, again,
this is after integration by parts,
and L'Hospital's Rule,
you get one over lambda,
and that's a famous result,
hopefully you remember that
from a probability class.
Here's a definition, or
actually it's a theorem
that you may not have seen before.
This is called the Law of
the Unconscious Statistician,
or LOTUS.
And this is a very, very
important nice little result.
We'll kind of pretend it's a definition,
but in fact it's a theorem.
So, this just gives us the expected value
of sort of an arbitrary function of X,
let's call that arbitrary function h of X,
and it can kind of be anything,
I'll give you some examples in a minute.
But the expected value of h of X,
this is a general definition now,
is, in the discrete case,
its summation over all X
of h of X of f of X,
that's if X is discrete.
And if X is continuous,
it's the integral over all X
of h of X times f of X dx, again,
wherever you see a summation,
put an integral sign
for the continuous case.
Here's my shorthand notation.
Integral over the real line
of h of X times d f of X.
Like I said, the function
h of X can be anything,
kind of nice.
For example, h of X equals
X squared or one over X,
or sin of X or log of X.
It can be anything nice.
Here's an example. Here's
a discrete example.
Suppose X has the following discrete
random variable distribution.
X can equal two, three, or four,
with probabilities 0.3,
0.6, and 0.1, respectively.
Let's suppose, for some reason,
we wanna calculate the
expected value of X cubed.
So, h of X equals X cubed,
and we plug in to my equation
the expected value of X
cubed is just sum over all X
of X cubed times f of X,
I plug in the three different
values that X can take,
namely, X equals two, three, and four,
so here's X cubed, two cubed times f of X,
f of two is 0.3, plus
three cubed times 0.6,
plus 4 cubed times 0.1,
and after a little algebra,
you get 25.
What could be easier?
Here's another example.
Suppose that X is Uniform 0.2,
now I'll go for the whole thing
instead of the expected value of X cubed,
let's just be arbitrary
and get the expected value
of X to the nth power.
So that's gonna be,
using the Law of the
Unconscious Statistician,
integral over the real line of X to the n
times f of X,
so since it's a uniform distribution,
I only have to integrate from zero to two,
and then f of X is one half,
and after the smoke clears there,
my answer is two to the
n divided by n plus one.
So, since we saw that thing,
the expected value of X to the n,
let's actually define that
because it's quite useful.
The expected value of X to the n
is actually called the nth moment of X.
The slightly more complicated thing,
the expected value of the
following messy, awful function,
is the expected value of X minus E of X,
that whole thing to the nth power,
that's called the nth central moment.
Now, even though it
looks awful, don't panic.
That number E of X is just a number.
And so, this messy thing
inside X minus a number
to the nth power,
that's just a complicated,
big old h of X function.
That's called the nth central moment of X.
And that just sort of a
specialty case of moments.
The most special case
is the variance of X.
That's defined as the
second central moment,
and you can see it's the expected value
of the squared deviation
of X from its mean.
Now what does that mean?
E of X, the thing in the middle there,
is the expected value of X.
X minus E of X is how far
does the random variable
tend to deviate from the mean.
Now that could be plus or minus,
so let's square it and take the average
over all those values.
And you get the variance.
So, whereas the expected
value of X is a measure of,
sort of the middle of the distribution,
the variance of X is a measure
of how much the
distribution is spread out.
You may be familiar with
the standard deviation of X,
that's just the positive
square root of the variance.
And here's a theorem that I always like to
calculate the variance of X with.
After a little bit of algebra,
it turns out that you can
calculate the variance
simply by using the
expected value of X squared
minus the square of the mean.
That's just an easier way to
calculate variance sometimes.
As an example, let's suppose that X is
our good friend, the
Bernoulli distribution.
And you might want to remember that
the expected value of that X equals p.
Then it turns out that the
expected value of X squared is,
by the Law of the
Unconscious Statistician,
it's a summation of X squared times f of X
when you substitute in
the zero and the one,
turns out that's equal to p.
And so then the variance of X equals,
using my formula from the last page,
the expected value of X squared
minus E of X quantity squared
that's gonna be p minus p squared,
and that simplifies to
p times one minus p.
Let's be a little more ambitious,
let's look at the exponential distribution
with parameter lambda.
By the Law of the
Unconscious Statistician,
the expected value of
X to the nth power is
the integral over the real line,
in this case you only have
to go from zero to infinity,
'cause that's the only
place where X is defined,
of X to the n times lambda
E to the minus lambda X.
That's X e n f of X d exit,
and after you do the calculus,
now you may recognize this as
what's called a gamma function
or you may have recognized
your integral tables,
but believe it or not, after the algebra,
this comes out to be n
factorial over lambda to the n.
That's sort of a famous result.
In particular, the variance
of X equals E of X squared
minus E of X quantity squared,
that's gonna be if I plug
in to the above equation
n equals two, that gives
me two over lambda squared
minus the square of the mean,
we've already calculated
the mean as one over lambda,
after I do the algebra there,
the variance of X equals
one over lambda squared.
That's sort of a famous result.
Okay, fantastic.
Here's a general theorem.
It shows that expectation
is a linear function.
So what I mean by that is,
the expected value of aX plus b equals,
well just move the expected value inside.
a times the expected value of X plus b,
so just move the expected value inside.
Doesn't quite work out
like that for the variance.
The variance of aX plus b equals
a squared times the variance of X.
So the a comes outside as an
a squared, the b goes away.
Let's think about that.
If I have a random variable,
and I just shift it by b,
that's not gonna change
how much it's spread out.
It's just gonna affect
where it's centered.
So, that b doesn't come into play
when I look at the variance.
Here's an example,
let's supposed that X is
exponential three, lambda
equals three from the last page,
the expected value then
of minus two X plus seven,
I just made that up,
is, well let's bring the expected
value inside, like I said,
so minus two, expected
value of X plus seven,
the expected value of
X is one over lambda,
one over three,
so that's where I get
this minus two thirds,
and then I'm so totally lazy,
I'm just gonna keep the plus seven there.
If you have extra time
during commercials tonight,
you can calculate minus two
thirds plus seven for yourself.
The variance, meanwhile, well
minus two is my value of a,
it comes outside as minus two squared,
so that's gonna be four
times the variance of X,
so that's where that four comes from.
The variance of X is
one over lambda squared,
so that's four over nine.
So very, very easy.
Let's take a tiny little
break here, just a moment.
And, turns out, we've just gotten through
a bunch of good stuff with
respect to expectations.
And now I'm gonna do one more topic,
this is sort of a bonus topic.
I'd like you to take a
look at it carefully,
but this really is a bonus topic,
and turns out it's very useful
for a variety of reasons,
and these are called moment
generating functions.
And it's a little more challenging,
that's why I decided to take
this little break for a second.
Okay, break's over.
So, here's a definition of a
moment generating function.
M X of t equals the expected
value of e to the t X.
Now it looks a little awful,
but that's what the moment
generating function is, mgf.
So it turns out, M X of
t is a function of t,
not explicitly of X.
I mean, once you define
the random variable, X,
the moment generating function
for the random variable, X,
is just the expected value
of e to the t X, it's a function of t.
Here's an example.
Now, we don't panic, we're just gonna use
the Law of the Unconscious Statistician.
Let's let X equal our friend
the Bernoulli distribution
with parameter, p.
So, the mgf, M X of t is, by definition,
the expected value of e to the t X,
by the Law of the
Unconscious Statistician,
it's the sum over all X of
e to the t X times f of X.
At this point, see it's
a discrete distribution,
so we use a summation,
not an integral sign,
that darn thing looks
like Laplace transform,
if you remember back to
your engineering days,
the only thing that's different is that
we have a t instead of a minus t.
So, if you remember Laplace transforms,
that's great, if you don't,
don't worry about it.
In any case, the only
two possible values of X
are zero and one.
Here's the X equals zero term,
e to the t zero times f of zero, that's q,
probability X equals
zero is q for Bernoulli,
and e to the t times one,
f of one, that's this term,
f of one is p,
after a little algebra,
you get the answer,
p e to the t plus q, pet q.
That's the answer.
As another example, let's
go continuous again.
Take the exponential distribution,
that's just 'cause it's easy for me.
M X of t equals the
integral over the real line
e to the t x f of X d X,
the integral only goes from
zero to infinity,
because that's where the
exponential is defined.
We have the e to the t X right there,
that's the e to the t X.
The e to the minus lambda X times lambda,
well there's the lambda right here,
here's the e to the minus
lambda X right there,
I take the integral of that thing,
and it's lambda over lambda minus t,
if lambda is greater than t.
The reason lambda has to
be greater than t is that
the darn thing will equal
infinity if that's not the case.
You'll get an issue.
Okay now why is the moment
generating function important?
Well, under certain technical conditions,
which I'm not gonna get into,
it turns out that the expected
value of X to the kth power
equals a function of the moment
generating function, wow.
In fact that function's
a little bit complicated,
it looks like a Christmas tree.
It's the kth derivative with
respect to t of the mgf,
M X of t evaluated at t equals zero.
And you gotta do things in that order.
Take the kth derivative of the mgf,
then shove in t equals zero,
and you're gonna come up
with the expected value
of X to the kth power.
So, in other words, you
can generate moments of X
from the moment generating function.
Isn't it amazing why they named it that.
So the moment generating
function's got a lot
of other important uses,
but in particular in
identifying distributions
and proving convergence in some things,
we'll talk about those a
little bit later in the course.
But for right now, the
mgf generates moments.
What a surprise.
Here's an example let's look
at the exponential distribution
you might remember from
a couple pages ago,
that the mgf is lambda
over lambda minus t,
let's take the expected value of that.
Let's get the expected value
of the exponential distribution
Well, from the previous theorem,
it's the first derivative of M X of t
evaluated at t equals zero.
The first derivative of
lambda over lambda over t,
we can do this in our heads,
turns out is lambda over
lambda minus t squared.
Just use the chain rule.
Evaluate that at t equals zero.
So I shove in the t equals zero,
I get lambda over lambda
minus zero squared
which is one over lambda.
It looked like a lot of work,
but this is actually a little less work
than going and using L'Hospital's Rule
and integration by parts, and all that.
So, this is actually a quicker way
to get the expected value, in my opinion.
If you wanna get expected
value of X squared,
well just play the game again.
Take the second derivative and that's just
two times lambda over
lambda minus t cubed,
again, we do the chain rule, very easy.
Set t equals zero and plug in,
and you get two over lambda squared.
And this immediately
gives you the variance,
expected value of X squared
minus E of X quantity squared
blah, blah, blah, equals
one over lambda squared.
So that's an old result,
and I think we actually,
we were able to do this
a little bit more quickly this way.
So, here's a summary of
what we did in this lesson.
Did lots of expectations,
I just love using LOTUS.
We'll be using LOTUS all
the time in this course.
And it's especially useful
in terms of simulation,
you'll see why later.
Next time, let's suppose I know
everything there is to know
about the random variable,
in this lesson, we just
looked at expected values,
that's kind of small stuff.
Suppose we know everything, we
know the whole distribution.
Well, what happens if we square
the thing or take the log?
So, what I'm gonna do
now, in the next lesson,
we'll look at arbitrary
functions of random variables,
and these play huge roles in simulation.
(gleam)