- Hi everyone,
so we're still continuing
the probability boot camp.
And in this lesson, we'll be talking about
jointly distributed random variables
because one is just never enough.
Here's our lesson overview,
in the last lesson we looked at
functions of random variables,
and in particular, we looked
at the inverse transform method
for generating random
variable from uniforms,
which has tremendous
implications in simulation.
In this lesson,
we'll look at two
dimensional random variables
that may or may not be
correlated with each other.
Think about height and
weight, for instance.
And in simulation, I think
about things like consecutive,
correlated waiting times.
So if we have customers
in a line, obviously,
the waiting times between
customers are going to be
correlated with each other.
So here's the idea,
let's consider two
random variables for now,
interacting together, let's
think height and weight.
So let's look at the definition
of the joint cdf of X and Y,
two random variables, so that's capital
F of (x, y), capital F for the cdf,
that equals the probability that X
is less than or equal to little x,
Y is less than or equal
to little y, jointly.
We're looking at the two random variables,
x and y, simultaneously.
Here's the remark then,
the marginal cdf of X is
the cdf of X just by itself,
so marginal means, just by itself.
So you can think of F of
(x) as the probability that
X is less than or equal to little x, well,
if I let Y equal to infinity,
in the joint cdf definition,
that's the probability that
X is less than or equal to
little x, Y is less than
or equal to infinity.
So that's the same thing
as X all by itself.
I'm using the subscript
capital X to remind us
it's just X all by itself.
Similarly, the marginal
cdf of Y all by itself,
capital F of subscript
y, that's the joint cdf
evaluated, X equals
infinity, and little y.
Another definition now,
if capital X and capital Y
are discrete random variables,
then the joint pmf probability
mass function of X and Y
is little F of (x) equals
the probability that
capital X equals little x,
capital Y equals little y.
So, that completely defines
the joint probability
mass function of X and Y.
In fact, if you add up all
those possible F of (x)
y values, you'll get one.
Just as before, for the cdf
we can calculate the marginal pmf of x,
and that's just the
pmf of x all by itself,
little F of (x) equals
the probability that
capital X equals little x.
And by, you may remember the
law of total probability,
the way you get that is
you take the joint pmf,
and just add up all the possible y values.
For all the y's, you add
them up, you get f of (x).
Similarly, the marginal pmf
of Y, Fy is the probability
that Y equals little y,
that's just the sum over all
x values of the joint pmf.
So you fix y, and add up
all the possible x values,
and you get the probability
that Y equals little y.
Now, you'll see what I'm talking about
when we do a numerical example.
This table gives the joint
probability mass function,
f of (x, y), for a little,
simple example that I thought of.
Very simple.
And we have the possible values of X are
two, three, and four.
Right here.
The possible values of Y are four and six,
I just made these up.
The numbers in the interior of the table
give the joint pmfs.
So for instance,
the probability that X
equals two and Y equals for
is point three, same with
the other five entries.
They add up, these
interior entries, to one.
You add them all up, you get one.
Now, here's why we call little f of (x),
little f of (y), marginals.
So here's little f of (x)
and it's called the marginal
probability mass function
because if I were to take
all the y values for say,
x equals two,
add them up,
I get point three, plus point one,
equals point four.
That corresponds to the
probability that x equals two.
So I added up all the y
values when x equals two
and I got the marginal value,
probability that x equals two.
And turns out, it was point four.
Similarly, I get x equals
three, x equals four,
and so that completely defines the
probability mass function for x,
and namely, it's point four,
point four, and point two,
for x equals two, three,
and four, respectively.
And that adds up to one,
because it's a probability mass function.
Same thing with y,
the probability that y
equals four, is point six,
equals six, is point four,
I just added up all the
x values along the row.
So very, very nice.
Here's the continuous
version of these definitions.
If X and Y are continuous,
then the joint pdf,
probability density function,
of X and Y,
is given by this nasty looking thing,
little f of (x, y) equals
the second partial derivative
of capital F of (x, y).
So just take my word for that
and note that if I take
the double integral of
f of (x, y), dxdy, that equals one,
that corresponds to adding
up in two dimensions
all the x and y probabilities
in the discrete case.
I can get the marginals of X and Y.
The marginal pdf of X is
given by f of (x) equals
the integral, over all
values of y of f of (x, y),
that corresponds to adding
up, in the discrete case,
all the f of (x, y)
values, over all the y's,
to get the marginal pmf of x.
So here's the marginal pdf
of x that's just the integral
over all y of f of (x, y).
The marginal pdf of y,
similarly, is integral of
x of f of (x, y), dx.
So I'm integrating out the x's,
and I'm just left with
the function of the y's.
Here's an example,
and I'll be using this
example for a while.
Let's suppose that the
joint pdf is given by
f of (x, y) equals 21
over four, x squared, y.
And this is for all y values
between x squared and one.
This is a legitimate pdf,
if I take the double integral
over all the (x, y) values
satisfying x squared less
than y less than one,
this thing does, in
fact, integrate to one.
It's a little bit tricky,
because of these limits,
the limits are x squared,
less than y, less than one.
I call these funny limits,
I'll be using that
expression occasionally.
Funny, as in strange, not ha-ha.
So this is the joint pdf,
the darn thing does integrate to one.
Here's the marginal.
Marginal of x is given by
integral over all values
of y of f (x, y) and
here's where we have
to be a little careful,
the limits of y are from x squared to one.
So let's slavishly plug that in.
Integral from x squared
to one of f of (x, y) is
21 over four, x squared, y.
After the smoke clears,
you get 21 over eight, x squared,
times 1 minus x to the fourth.
Now, that is for x between
negative one and one.
Where did the y go?
Well I integrated it out, it's gone.
So, after I get rid of the y,
I'm just left with the limits of x squared
having to be less than one,
and that's the same thing as negative one
less than x, less than one.
That's how I got that.
The marginal for y, similarly,
f of (y) equals integral
of f of (x, y), dx.
Now, if x squared is less
than y, is less than one,
well, that means that x squared
runs from negative square root of y
to plus square root of y.
It looks a little bit tricky,
but that's what it is.
And after the smoke clears there,
I'm left with 7 halves, y to the 5 halves.
And there are no x's anymore
because this is the marginal y's and
I've integrated the x's out.
That just means that y
is between zero and one.
Because I got rid of all
of the x's in my limits.
That's where I get zero
less than y, less than one.
The nice thing is,
I can integrate this pdf,
7 halves y to the 5 halves,
in my head between zero and one,
and the darn thing integrates
to one, just like I promise.
It's a legitimate pdf.
Here's the definition.
X and Y are independent
random variables if
f of (x, y) equals f of (x)
times f of (y) for all x and y.
This corresponds to the same
definition of independence
we had way, way long ago
when we started our review.
Here's the theorem,
X and Y are independent if
you can write their joint pdf
as a function of x times a function of y.
I'm calling that a(x) times b(y).
Just for any old a(x) and b(y).
This is all fine and good,
but sometimes it looks
like you can write it as
a of (x) times b of (y),
but if the darn thing has funny limits,
that's why I keep on
saying the darn thing,
then these guys are not independent.
So if you can write it as
a of (x) times b of (y),
that's great,
but don't forget the funny
limits if they're there.
And I'll give examples in a
second, to show you what I mean.
So, funny limits cause a lot of trouble.
In the previous example that I did,
again, I'll show you that in a minute,
we had funny limits.
So, here are a bunch of examples.
Let's let f of (x, y) equal cxy,
for zero less than x, less than two,
zero less than y, less than three.
What's nice here is that, look at that,
a(x) times b(y), very
simple, no funny limits.
These guys are independent,
that's an easy one.
How about this? This is
our previous example,
from a couple pages ago.
Look at that, I can write a(x) times b(y),
but hold on, funny limits.
So that means that x and y
are not independent, too bad.
And finally,
here's f of (x, y) equals c over x plus y.
The reason I say c,
is because I'm too lazy
to figure out what the
appropriate consonant is gonna be.
C over x plus y, that you
cannot write as a function
of a(x) times b(y), so too bad,
they're not independent.
Notice that I didn't
have funny limits here,
but so what, I couldn't
write that as a function
of a(x) times b(y) so, not independent.
Too bad.
Let's give another definition,
the conditional probability
density function or
probability mass function of
Y, given X equals little x,
is just like, when we
were doing the initial
probability review,
it's f of (x, y) over f of (x),
and that assumes that
x is greater than zero.
This is a legitimate probability mass or
probability density function.
For instance, in the continuous case,
the thing integrates to one,
just like it's supposed to.
So if I integrate over all values of y,
that will integrate to
one for any given x.
And I'll motivate that a
little more in a second.
Here's an example, if f of
(x, y) equals our old friend,
21 over four, x squared, y,
for x squared less than y, less than one,
then f of (y) given x, is, by definition,
f of (x, y) over f of (x),
I plug and chug all this mess here,
this is 21 over four, x squared,
y, that's my f of (x, y),
here's f of (x), which we
calculated a couple pages ago.
I do the algebra, and here's my answer.
Two, y, over one minus x to the fourth.
And this is for y between
x squared, and one.
I did nothing to get rid of the x value,
I mean, those x's are
there because I told you,
I've got this information about x,
so of course it should be included in the
conditional pdf.
These conditional distributions
are very, very important.
If X and Y are independent,
then it turns out that
f of (y), given x, equals f
of (y) for all of x and y.
So what this means, is
that information about x,
contributes nothing to
the distribution of y.
So this might be one of these cases where,
what's the IBM stock price today,
given the fact that it's
thirty degrees on Mars?
Well, the information
x equals 30 degrees has
no impact, at all, on the IBM stock price.
Or is that what we're told to believe.
So here's a quick proof.
F of (y), given x
equals, by definition,
f of (x, y) over f of (x).
Now, if x and y are
independent, then f of (x, y)
equals f of (x) times f of (y),
by definition of independence.
And then, the f of (x)'s
on top and bottom cancel,
and I'm done.
So that's the end of
the proof, very simple.
This is gonna lead me
now to the conditional
expectation of Y given X equals little x.
If you're willing to
believe that I can give you
the conditional pdf or pmf of Y given X,
then I can take the expected
value of that updated
information of Y.
And again, I'll motivate in a second.
Here's the definition,
the conditional expectation
of Y given X equals little x
is in the discrete case,
summation of y times f of (y) given x,
in the continuous case, integral,
of y times f of (y) given
x, and that's taken over dy.
X is fixed, and we
integrate, or sum, the y's.
Now, this is a very,
very important concept.
Because what it allows
us to do is to update
our information about y,
after we've heard about x.
So for example, let's suppose
I've got a guy in the room
and he's seven feet tall,
and I'm interested in his expected weight.
The information that he's seven feet tall,
is going to give me an
expected value for his weight,
an expected value of y,
given that x equals seven.
That's probably going
to be greater than the
expected weight of some
totally random guy,
with no information about his height.
Now, that would be the
expected value of y,
that's total, random
guy from the population,
no knowledge at all about his height,
that's going to give me a
different expected value
for weight, than somebody
who's height I already know.
Here's our old continuous example,
that we've seen nine
thousand times already.
Let's let f of (x, y) equal 21 over four,
x squared, y, x squared
less than y, less than one.
Here's the conditional expected value,
by definition, it equals the
integral over the real line
of y times f of (y) given x.
I plug in f of (y) given x,
that's two y squared over
one minus x to the fourth times y.
I integrate y between x squared and one,
and after the algebra, here's my answer.
Two-thirds, one minus x to the sixth over
1 minus x to the fourth.
And this is actually for x
between negative one and one.
Notice it's perfectly
okay to have an x here,
because in fact, the
expected value of y is
a function of little x.
The expected weight is a
function of the height.
So it's perfectly okay to have
that nasty looking expression.
So here's a summary of what
we just did in this lesson.
We did a lot of stuff with
joint pmf's and pdf's,
we looked at independents,
we looked at conditional distributions,
we even looked at conditional expectation,
that's a lot of stuff.
Next time, I'm gonna continue the fun,
with conditional expectation,
including something I call double trouble.
This is by far the hardest lesson
that we'll do in the boot camp.
I want you to see it, I'm
not gonna have you repeat it
verbatim ever, but I
do want you to see it.
So really looking forward to next time,
it's gonna be a lot of fun.