- Hi everybody.
We're now going to continue in module two
with integration as we go
through our calculus primer.
Here is the lesson overview.
So, last time, we went through
a couple of different ways
to find zero of a complicated function.
That was nice.
We learned a couple of
ways that we'll be using
throughout the rest of the course.
Now, we'll kinda do what
goes up, must come down.
A couple lessons ago,
we reviewed derivatives,
now we're gonna go the other direction.
We're gonna do integration.
And again, this is the situation
where I hope that you'll
remember a lot of old friends.
Let's make the fundamental definition
that a function, capital f of x,
having derivative, little f of x,
is called the antiderivative.
The antiderivative is
denoted, capital f of x
equals the integral,
that little sign there
is the integral sign,
of f of x, d x, and it's also
called the indefinite integral
of little f of x.
So, there's a couple ways that
you can say the notations.
This is the fundamental
theorem of calculus.
If little f of x is continuous,
then the area under the
curve, over the interval a, b
is denoted and given by what's
called the definite integral.
Integral from a to b of f, of x, d x
that's equal to, and this is notation,
capital f of x, the big straight up thingy
evaluate a and b.
That's just the way you say it.
This is equal to capital f
of b minus capital f of a.
That's the fundamental
theorem of calculus.
This relates the derivative
of a function capital f of x
and it relates it to the
antiderivative little f of x.
So, everything's all nice
what you would expect.
The reason they call
it a definite integral,
is because it's really,
really an integral.
Here are some old friends.
Just like we looked at the
friends of the derivatives,
here are the friends involving integrals.
So, the indefinite integral
of x to the k power,
is x to the k, plus one
over k, plus one, plus c.
C is an arbitrary constant,
because you'll see that
when you take the derivative
of x to the k, plus one over k, plus one
that c, just becomes a zero.
So, I'm gonna have that c every place.
And I'll give you a little mnemonic
to remember that in a minute.
This particular integral holds
for all k not equal to one.
For k equal to negative one.
For k equal to negative one,
we have to look at the special
case, integral of d x over x.
It turns out that's the natural log
of absolute value of x plus c.
We'll look at a mnemonic
for that in a little while.
The reason for this is
there's some convergence
and divergence issues
which only take place
when k equals minus one,
so let's just remember that.
Now, if the derivative
e to the x is e to the x
then the integral of e to the
x, d x is e to the x plus c.
Similarly, the integral of
cosine equals sine plus c.
Because, remember when we took
the derivative of sine we got cosine.
And the integral of one
over one plus x squared,
is equal to arctan plus c.
So, these are just, there's
a million of these things.
I just gave a few that you might remember.
Here's an example.
And this is that mnemonic
I was talking about.
It's very easy to see from
the previous argument,
that since the integral
of d x over x is log of x,
then the integral of d cabin
over cabin, is log cabin.
Pretty funny math joke.
But, the reason I'm giving you this
is because I want you
to remember that plus c,
the arbitrary constant.
And then we remember that log cabin plus c
is equal to houseboat.
So that's just something to keep in mind,
and I'm sure you'll remember
that the rest of your lives.
Theorem.
Some well-know properties
of definite integrals are as follows.
The integral of f of x, d x from a to a,
so think of the area under this continuous
function under one point.
There is no area.
So, it's zero.
The integral from a to b
is negative of the integral from b to a.
And finally, the integral from a to b
plus the integral, equals
the integral from a to c
plus the integral from c to b.
So, if you stop taking the
integral at some midpoint, c,
and then you start up again,
when you add those two pieces up
you just get the whole thing from a to b.
Here's some other properties
of general integrals.
The integral of the sum is
the sum of the integrals.
This is sort of the
analogous to the product
rule and derivatives.
And this is called integration by parts.
Integral of f times g prime equals f of x
times g of x minus integral
of g times f prime.
That's called integration by parts.
'Cause we're breaking
things up into f and g.
And finally, this is sort of
reminiscent of the chain rule.
The integral of f of g of x times g prime
is equal to f of u, d u.
That's the substitution rule,
where we take u equal to g of x.
We got to be a little bit careful here,
because this substitution
of u of x equal to g of x
will possibly change the
limits of integration.
But it's something you should remember.
And here's a couple mnemonics
that will help you remember.
You can go look them up on the web.
Let's use integration by parts
with f of x equal to x
and g prime of x equal to e to the two x.
And then we'll also use
the chain rule, as well.
So, integral of x times e to the two x.
So, this thing
you can see that I'm
associating x with f of x
and e to the two x with g prime of x.
When you use this integration by parts,
one of the tricks is just figuring out
what's the f of x part
what's the g prime of x part.
So, according to integration by parts,
the first term is gonna
be f of x times g of x,
which is f of x is x.
G of x, the integral of g prime
which is integral of e to the two x
is gonna be e to the two x over two.
I needed the chain rule for that.
So, that first term,
x times e to the two x over two
evaluate at zero and one.
And then subtract off g
of x times f prime of x.
And g of x is e to the two x over two,
f prime equals one.
And so what I have.
I do my substitution of zero and one
into that first term with
the big vertical thingy,
and then I subtract off the integral.
And I get e squared over
two after I substitute.
Now I do the integral.
That turns out to be minus
e to the two x over four,
evaluate at zero and one.
And there's my answer.
e to the two, e squared
plus one over four.
When the smoke clears.
A pretty easy example.
Let's give another definition.
Derivatives of arbitrary
order k can be written as
f, k in parentheses of x
or d k, d x k, f of x.
And by convention we let f not
just be the same as f of x.
So one nice thing, which we'll
use a couples times in class,
is that you can write f of x
in what's called a Taylor series expansion
about a point a and it's
given by this infinite sum,
sum from k equal to zero
of the k'th derivative
evaluated at a times x minus a
to the k'th power over k factorial.
That's what's called a
Taylor series expansion,
and it's quite nice.
It's used occasionally.
Maclaurin series is just the Taylor series
expanded around a equals zero.
Now without going into huge detail
here are some Maclaurin friends.
You may remember this.
Sine of x, if I do all those derivatives
in the previous slide, can be
written as that infinite sum.
The first one.
Cosine of x, the second infinite sum,
and e to the x, is the third one.
They all look a little messy
but they're really not bad at all
and they're actually kind of famous.
And while we're at it,
'cause I'm looking at all these sums.
Here are three that
have nothing to do with
these Taylor series, really,
but these are just things that come up
every once in a while.
So this is as good a place
as any to talk about 'em.
If I'm interested in adding up
all the values of k from one to n,
that's just n times n plus one over two.
This is something that
Gauss was able to do
when he was five or six
years old, believe it or not.
If I want to add up all
the values of k squared,
you get n times n plus one,
times two n plus one, over six.
That's famous.
And if I have this
infinite geometric series,
I want to add up p to the k
from k equals zero infinity,
and turns out that that's
just one over one minus p.
And that's something
that you probably learned
in high school, but it bears repeating.
So one last thing we'll talk
about is L'Hospital's Rule.
Every once in a while we get into trouble
when we have something of the form
zero over zero or infinity over infinity.
So sometimes, L'Hospital's Rule's useful
because it turns out that zero over zero
or infinity over infinity,
they could equal anything.
So here's what it says,
if the limits f of x as x goes to a,
and g of x as x goes to a,
both go to zero or go to infinity,
then the limit of x goes to a,
a limit as x goes to a,
of f of x over g of x, equals the limit
as x goes to a of f prime
of x over g prime of x.
And it looks liked we're
complicating things
but sometimes this
rule, L'Hospital's Rule,
makes things a lot easier.
And this rule makes me
sick, ha ha ha, L'Hospital.
So here's a quick example.
And this characterizes
why this things so useful.
So let's look at sine of x over x.
Now as x goes to zero, this is
a zero over zero type thing.
So turns out, let's take the derivative.
Derivative of the top,
sine of x is cosine of x.
The derivative of the
bottom, x is equal to one.
So I can now take the
limit is x goes to zero
of cosine of x over one,
is gonna be cosine of zero
over one, which is one.
So congratulations, you've just shown
sine of x over x goes to one.
Again you gotta be a little careful
because these zero over zero things
or infinity over infinity
can go to any quantity.
You've gotta be very careful about that.
Here's a summary of what we just did.
We've renewed acquaintances
with a bunch of old integral friends
and we looked at some
elementary properties,
including L'Hopsital's Rule.
Next time, I'm gonna look at
some numerical integration techniques
and I want to see what happens
when I can't do the integrals
in those nice, close form.
So what do we do if those friends
don't wanna come out and play with us?
And anyway, we'll see ya next time.