- Hi, everyone.
So now, we're gonna be moving
into some integration techniques
when you can't get the
answer in closed form.
So, this lesson is entitled,
Integration Computer Exercises.
You'll see why.
Here's the overview.
Last time I did this wonderful,
puntastic integration review.
And you'll see for yourselves
when you go through that last lesson.
This time, I'm gonna implement several,
what are called, numerical techniques,
that you might need if you can't
get those beautiful printed
closed-form solutions
to a particular integral.
Which happens every once and awhile.
And one of these techniques
actually incorporates simulation.
I'm just gonna give you a
hint as to how that works
and we'll do that in gross
and tedious detail a little bit later.
As an exercise, let's do
some very easy integration
via what I call Riemann sums.
And here what we're gonna do,
is we'll simply approximate the area
under this nice beautiful,
continuous function,
f of x from a to b,
just by adding up the areas
of n adjacent rectangles.
And you might remember from calculus class
that let's say these rectangles
evenly divide the
interval ab into n pieces,
so n as in Nancy.
And so, the width of each
rectangle is gonna be,
we'll call it delta x.
And that's just b minus a over n.
And the height of the
rectangle is f of xi,
where xi is one of the points
inside each of the rectangles.
So xi in this case could
be a lot of things.
So, I'm gonna take it equal
to a plus i times delta x.
That's the right hand n
point of the ith rectangle.
So you can picture me writing
little adjacent rectangles
next to each other under the curve
and those rectangles are
approximately equal the curve.
So, the integral from a to b of f of x dx
is approximately equal to
the sum of the areas of the rectangles.
The height of the rectangle is f of xi
and the width of the rectangle is delta x.
So, what I've said now
is that as Riemann did,
I can approximate the integral
by this very simple
summation of rectangles.
And now to simplify things a little bit,
looks a little bit nastier,
but these are actual simplifications.
Delta x, I'm just taking the same
for each of the rectangles.
It's b minus a over n,
instead of having x of i,
I'm substituting a plus
i times b minus a over n.
That's x of i.
And the nice thing about this is,
as n goes to infinity for
nicely behaved functions,
the right hand side of this mess
equals the left hand side.
That's as n goes to infinity.
The rectangles get skinnier and skinnier
and they eventually approximate the area
under the curve really well.
We've sorta seen that in
some of the demos I've given.
So, let's try this out on the
integral from zero to one.
A sign of pi x over 2dx.
We've sorta seen this before.
It's secretly equals two over pi,
which is 0.6366.
And I'm gonna do this for
different values of n.
Actually, I'll write down for one
and then you can see for
yourself for other values.
Okay, here we go.
Since I'm a very nice guy
I'm gonna try to make
things as easy as possible.
And I'm gonna take a equals
zero and b equals one.
And that just simplifies things.
So instead of writing delta
x equals b minus a over n,
b is one, a is zero,
then delta x is just one over n.
And xi is i over n.
So this simplifies things.
So what we have is, integral
from a to b, f of x dx,
just equals, like I promised,
integral from zero to one
of f of x.
And that approximately
equals, by that 2nd equation
on the previous page,
summation f of xi delta x.
Delta x is b minus a over n,
which is one minus zero over n,
so that's where we get the one over n.
F of xi, well f of x is
sine of pi, x over two.
So you can see how I've got
the sine of pi over two,
and the x is just i over n.
So let's take n equals 100,
get Excel or whatever out,
don't do it by hand,
'cause there's 100 of 'em.
This calculates out to a value of .6416,
which is actually pretty
close to that true answer
of two over pi, which
is approximately .6366.
If I made n bigger, I'm gonna
get closer to that answer.
And maybe you can try that out at home.
Here's another computer exercise.
This is the trapezoid version.
Now we're gonna do
the same type of numerical
integration problem,
except now I'm using the trapezoid rule,
which is usually a little bit better
than this Riemann summation.
Now we have integral
from a to b of f of x dx,
that equals this more
complicated function.
In the middle there,
there's still this summation
from i equals one to n minus one,
so the sum now instead of
going from i equals zero to n,
goes from i equals one to
n minus one of f of xi.
But now we have these end
points f of x naught over two,
f of xn over two, and so it turns out
if you draw the little picture,
instead of having rectangles,
you have sort of little trapezoids now.
This mess simplifies
down to the next line,
b minus a over n, times the
giant thing in brackets.
And I'm not gonna have you
actually go through an example right now.
You might wanna try this out at home
on the same integral, zero to
one, sine of pi x over two.
You'll get pretty much the same answer,
except it turns out you
get a little bit faster
for a smaller values of
n converge the answer
two over pi a little bit more quickly.
You can try this out yourself.
It's not that hard.
Okay now, the thing that
interests me the most,
and in fact this is a simulation class,
we're gonna learn in more detail
a Monte Carlo simulation method
to accomplish the same
approximate integration.
So I'm gonna have you just
take my word for it for now,
but we'll get into this
in more detail later on.
I just wanna show you what
we're dealing with here.
Let's suppose that I can
generate a series of independent,
identically distributed random numbers,
uniform random numbers
between zero and one.
If you don't remember
what a uniform number is
between zero and one,
it's just a random real
number between zero and one.
You can use Excel, the
function RAND, what a surprise.
How do we use these random numbers
between zero and one to
approximate the integral?
It turns out that with
just a little bit of work,
and we'll go through this
in tedious detail later on,
the integral from a to b of f of x dx
is approximately equal
to b minus a over n,
that looks familiar.
Times the summation from x equals one to n
of f of a plus b minus a use of i.
This looks a lot like the Riemann integral
except what's going on
is that these are not gonna be rectangles
that are right next to each other.
These are gonna be rectangles
that are randomly placed
between a and b.
Take my word for it for now.
And it turns out, this converges
at about the same speed
as Riemann, to the correct answer,
namely integral from a to b of f of x.
And if you want, you can
go home and try this out
on the same integral that
we've been working with
but you'll be given adequate
practice with this later on.
Here's a summary.
This time we went over
some very easy numerical
integration techniques.
And right at the end I
snuck in a little simulation
while you weren't looking,
we snuck it in there.
Next time I'm just gonna make a guess
that it's very, very likely
that we're gonna be starting
our probability primer.
You might say it's probable.
So we'll see ya then.