- Hi everyone!
Well, now we're about to begin module two,
which is basically a series of boot camps
on calculus, probability, and statistics.
We're done with the easy stuff,
we've done a little tour,
now we're gonna get to do a little math,
but hopefully it's
mostly a review for you.
So here's the lesson overview for now.
In the last module I gave
a very high-level overview
of what simulation is, that was our tour,
and this time the module
is going to present
these various boot camps,
and I'm gonna start right now
with a calculus lesson.
Now here's the dirty little secret,
in fact there's nothing here
that you haven't taken before
if you've taken the prerequisites,
so don't worry too much,
just go with the flow
and let's see what we remember.
So we'll start our calculus primer now.
The goal here is just
to give a brief review
of these little tidbits
that we'll be using later on
throughout the entire course.
First of all, let's go
through a couple sort of
elementary definitions
that you might remember
from long time ago.
Let's suppose that f of x is a function
that maps different values of
x from a domain to a range,
and you can represent
this thing in shorthand,
f goes from X to Y, you've
probably seen that before.
Here's an example.
If f of x equals x
squared, a little parabola,
then this function takes
x-values from the real line R,
that's some more notation,
and it maps it to the nonnegative
portion of the real line,
we'll call that R plus.
So let's do a little definition here.
We'll say that a function
f of x is continuous
if for any x naught and x in the domain
we have that the limit as x
goes to x naught of f of x
equals f of x naught.
Now that limit just
denotes the familiar limit
that we're all used to
even in high school,
and we'll assume that f
of x is going to exist
for all the x in the domain.
So here's a simple example.
Let's let f of x equals three x squared,
now that's just a quadratic function,
that thing is obviously
continuous for all x.
Now the function f of x equals integer x,
that's the round down function,
some people call it the floor function,
that thing's got what's
called a jump discontinuity
at any integer, so for
instance 3.4 equals three,
3.5 equals three, et cetera et cetera,
then it jumps up to
four when we get to 4.0.
Here's another definition,
we needed continuity for this one,
if f of x is continuous,
then the derivative,
which we denote as d dx f of x,
or sometimes we call it f prime of x,
that's the limit as h goes
to zero of the following:
f of x plus h, minus f of x, over h.
Now that can also be
interpreted as a slope
because f of x plus h minus f of x,
that's kinda the rise
and divided by h, that's the run,
over the range x to x plus h,
so that can be interpreted as a slope,
or an instantaneous slope at any point x.
Now we'll assume that it exists
and it's well-defined for any given x,
but that thing is the derivative.
Here are some old friends.
So when you take the derivative
of a polynomial term,
x to the k, you may remember
that that derivative is
k times x to the k minus one.
If you don't remember,
go back to your calculus
book lickety split.
One nice derivative is e to the x,
e is that exponential constant
but e to the x, the derivative
of that stays the same,
e to the x.
It's kind of a neat property
but you can go back to your
calculus book and see why.
Sine of x, the derivative
of that is cosine of x,
and sort of complimentary to that,
cosine of x, the derivative
of that is minus sine of x,
that's just something
that you have to remember.
The natural log of x, the
derivative of that, is one over x,
we'll be using that in a
little while when we integrate.
And finally, this last old friend,
if for some reason you want the derivative
of arctangent of x, well that's
one over one plus x squared,
and believe it or not we'll be using that
a couple times in the course.
So, here are some well known
properties of derivatives,
and I'll just using these on and off,
just wanted to remind you of them.
First of all, derivatives
have this linearity property.
The derivative of a times f of x plus b,
well that's just equal to a
times the derivative of x,
the derivative of b,
well that's the derivative of a constant,
and that's zero so that goes away.
If you've got the sum of two functions
then the derivative of the sum
is the sum of the derivative.
So f of x plus g of x,
the derivative of that,
is the derivative of f
plus the derivative of g.
Very nice.
Here's what's called the product rule,
the derivative of the product
is this slightly complicated thing,
f prime of x times g,
plus f of x times g prime.
So that's just the product
rule, you have to remember it,
that'll be useful later on when
we do integration by parts.
Now we've got this quotient rule,
this is an interesting one,
the derivative of the quotient
is this mess on the right hand side,
so the derivative of f of x over g of x is
g times f prime minus f times g prime
over g squared.
That's a little bit hard to remember,
I'll go over a mnemonic in a second.
Finally, the chain rule, I'll
also give a reference on that,
that's the derivative of a
more complicated function.
So if we want the derivative
of f of another function g,
so we're kind of doing a
composition of functions,
the derivative of f of
g of x, that's equal to
the derivative of f evaluated
at g, now you take the inside,
kind of do this in a chain, times g prime.
So f g quantity prime equals
f prime of g times g prime.
It's kind of like a chain.
So here are a couple references,
the first one is a mnemonic
for the quotient rule.
So if you consider f of x
as Hi because it's on top,
it's in the numerator, and g of x as Ho,
cause it's in the denominator,
then the derivative of the
quotient can be expressed as
Ho dee Hi minus Hi dee Ho
over Ho Ho.
Think about that, but it's
an easy way to remember it.
And then the chain rule,
there's a reference that you
can go look up on YouTube.
Here's an example, cause
you know we went through
all these equations, time
to do a little example,
here's an easy one I could think of,
let's let f of x equal x squared
and we'll set g of x
equal to natural log of x,
let's just see what some of
these things end up equaling
when we do these derivative rules.
First of all let's do the product rule,
so what's the derivative
of f of x times g of x?
Well remember, we said
that this is gonna be the
f of x times g prime plus
f prime times g of x.
And let's see if that
turns out to be the case.
So the first equality is just a,
I've reexpressed the
derivative of f times g
as the derivative of x squared
times natural log of x,
so according to my product rule it's,
well we'll do f prime of x times g,
so f prime is two x,
g is natural log of x,
plus f of x times g prime,
this looks a little tricky
because all of a sudden we just have an x,
but it actually makes sense.
What's g prime?
The derivative of natural
log of x is one over x,
and so that's cancels out
partially with the x squared
and that leaves me with the x
and so that's how we get
that answer, very very easy.
How about the quotient rule?
F of x over g of x, prime,
so that's the derivative
of x squared over natural log of x,
well you do Ho dee Hi
minus Hi dee Ho over Ho Ho,
Ho Ho in the denominator is very easy,
that's just natural log
squared of x, that's easy.
So Ho dee Hi minus Hi dee Ho,
well let's do the dee Hi part first,
that's two x, Ho is natural log of x
so that's where we get the left
hand side of that numerator,
and then minus
Hi dee Ho,
well we've already done that,
that's minus x, so that's
where that comes from.
Okay how about f of g quantity prime,
so we're gonna need the chain rule,
and that's gonna be
two times g of x times g prime of x,
and that turns out to equal
two times natural log of x over x.
Again you can go and check
that out, it's very very easy,
very very simple.
Okay let's make a remark now.
If one derivative is good enough,
how about two derivatives?
The second derivative,
f double prime of x,
equals the derivative
of the first derivative,
so I can express it as
d dx of f prime of x,
and you can kinda think of
it as the slope of the slope,
and if you remember physics class,
if f of x is what we'll call position,
then f prime of x is usually
regarded as velocity,
and f double prime is acceleration,
so if we wanna be Isaac Newton,
we remember all this stuff.
Knowing the second derivative is very nice
because it's helpful in finding mins
and maxes of a function.
So it turns out that the
minimum or maximum of f of x
can only occur when the
slope of f of x is zero,
think about it, kinda makes sense.
In other words, only when
f prime of x equals zero,
let's pretend for now that that happens
at the specific values x equals x naught,
then if f double prime of
x naught is less than zero,
it turns out you get a max.
If f double prime of x
naught is greater than zero,
you get a minimum, that's known
as concave down, concave up,
and if f double prime
of x naught equals zero
you get a point of inflection,
that doesn't happen very often
but when it does you get real sick
and that's why it's called
a point of infection.
I'm gonna go through this
example pretty quickly,
then we'll talk again in the
next lesson about this one.
Let's find x that minimizes f of x equals
e to the two x plus e to the minus x.
It turns out that the
minimum can only occur
when the derivative equals zero,
and I can take the derivative
of that using the chain rule,
the derivative of the
first term, e to the two x,
think of it as e to the g of x,
when I take the derivative of that,
I get e to the g of x times g prime of x,
and so that gives me,
cause g prime is two,
I get two e to the two x,
similarly the minus sign comes down
from the e to the minus x,
so the second term in the
derivative f prime of x
is gonna be minus e to the minus x.
Anyway, take all that,
two times e to the two x
minus e to the minus x,
set that equal to zero
and then solve for x.
So that solution occurs when x naught,
after a little algebra, equals
minus 1/3 natural log of 2,
and it turns out it's very easy to show,
if I take the second derivative
that f double prime of x is
greater than zero for all x,
and so therefore x naught is the minimum.
Okay, great, done with that example.
And in fact, done with this lesson.
Here's a summary.
What we did here is
that we did a little bit
of calculus derivative
memories, very nice stuff,
I hope there were no surprises.
And next time, I'm gonna take
sort of that last example
and I'm gonna give some
numerical techniques
to solve nonlinear equations,
in particular I'll try to
solve these nonlinear equations
to find out what the zeroes are,
and this is always pretty interesting
and it's actually stuff
that we'll be using
throughout the course.
So, see you next time!