- Hi everybody, welcome back.
Today I'll be looking at
functions of a random variable
as I continue the probability primer.
Let's get into that.
The lesson overview for now is, well,
what did we do last time?
I looked at tons of moments,
and moment generating functions
and I hope we had a lot of fun there.
In this lesson, let's suppose I know
everything about a random variable,
not only the moments, just everything.
What can I say about functions
of the random variable?
In particular, what's the distribution
going to be looking like?
And this has absolutely huge
implications in this course,
especially in random variant generation.
Here's the problem in general.
Let's suppose I have a random variable, X,
and I completely know the
probability mass function
of the probability density function.
In either case, it's F of X.
Let's look at the function of
X, H of X, I'll call that Y.
We saw h of X notation when I
used LOTUS in the last lesson.
Let's let this arbitrary
function of X be denoted by Y
and what I want now is I want g of Y,
the PMF or PDF of Y.
So, I've got the PMF or PDF of X,
now what's the PMF or PDF
of that function of X.
It's very important. Here's some examples.
And, take my word on
this, that these work.
It turns out, if X is
normal, normal zero one,
we'll talk about that
distribution later on,
it so happens that if I
take the square of that
I get a chi-square distribution.
Even if you don't know what those are,
if I square a normal, I get a chi-square,
it's because of this lecture.
Now, let's look at a uniform distribution.
Let's suppose I start with a nice,
easy, uniform zero one distribution.
We've actually seen this.
If I take the function
negative one over Lambda,
a natural log of that
uniform, I get an exponential.
Amazing!
So, I start with a uniform.
I plug the uniform into
this little equation here.
Negative one over Lambda, natural log of U
and I miraculously get an
exponential Lambda distribution.
This has huge implications
in random variant generation.
So, let's start off with a
very easy, discrete example.
I'm gonna let X denote
the number of heads from two coin tosses
and I'm gonna derive
the PMF for this function of
X Y equals X cubed minus X.
So anyway, let's look
at the PMF of X first.
X is the PMF from two coin tosses,
so it can equal zero, one, or two,
with corresponding probabilities,
a quarter, a half, and a quarter.
So, let's look at the
corresponding values for Y.
If X equals zero, then Y equals
X cubed minus X equals zero.
If X equals one, then Y also equals zero.
And if X equals two, then Y equals
X cubed minus X equals six.
So, you can see, the values
of X equals zero and one
map into Y equals zero
and the value of X equals zero
maps into Y equals six.
So, what does this imply?
Let's add up the probabilities.
The probability the Y equals zero
is the probability that
X equals zero or one.
Add those up. A quarter plus
a half equals three quarters.
The only other possibility
for Y, is Y equals six.
The probability of that is one quarter.
I didn't have to do much thinking there.
That corresponds to X equals 2.
So, in other words, the probability that
Y equals zero is three quarters.
The probability that Y
equals six is one quarter.
That is my PMF of Y.
Very, very easy.
Let's do a continuous example.
This one's a little bit more challenging.
Now suppose X has PDF,
because it's continuous.
F of X equals absolute value of X.
This is gonna be defined for X
between negative one and one.
It looks like this, sort
of a reverse triangle.
It goes from minus one to one
and you can see that if you
take the integral of this thing,
you can almost see in your head
that it integrates to one.
It's a legitimate PDF.
Given that is my starting point,
let's find the PDF of the
function Y equals X squared.
Okay, well, here's what you do.
Here's how you find these things.
I'm gonna find the CDF first, CDF of Y.
Then, I'll take the derivative.
So, this is the usual way
you do these problems.
You find the CDF first, then
you take the derivative.
Here's the CDF.
Now, I want to do as
little thinking as possible
because I'm totally lazy,
so let's just kinda do
things by the book here.
The CDF of Y is capital G of Y
and that is, by definition,
the probability that
Y is less than or equal to little Y.
That's just by definition,
no thought whatsoever, okay?
Again, in my quest not to do any thinking,
let's just plug in. What is Y?
It's X squared, so that's the probability
that X squared is less than or equal to Y.
And, now, let's remember that
I only know stuff about X.
I know everything there
is to know about X.
I don't know this X squared stuff.
So, how do I transform X squared to X?
Well, you take the square root,
so that's what this next step is.
The probability that
X squared is less than
or equal to Y is the probability that
X is between negative square root of Y
and plus square root of Y.
We had to be a little careful
when we take the square root
to remember that minus part.
Okay, well, what is this now?
By definition, it's the
integral of F of X DX
from negative square root of Y
to plus square root of Y
and F of X is square root of X.
After a little algebra, you
get that result equals Y,
and so, I can get the PDF of Y
now by taking the derivative.
The derivative of the CDF is the PDF
and even I can take the derivative
of capital G of Y equals Y.
That's just little G of Y equals one.
And what that means then,
is that Y is uniform zero one
because that is the PDF of a uniform.
So, if you start out with F of X equals
absolute value of X,
from negative one to one;
I square it.
Unbelievably, I get a
uniform distribution.
And, maybe, I'll give you a
homework assignment on that sometime.
You'll see for yourself that it works.
Even if you use simulation,
you'll get a nice uniform distribution.
So, this phenomenon is related to
what's called the Inverse
Transform theorem.
This is a fantastic theorem that's used
all the time in simulation.
You'll see why in a little while.
Let's suppose that X is a
continuous random variable
and the CDF is denoted
capital F of X, as usual.
Unbelievably and amazingly
and stupendously,
capital F of capital X, so this thing
is a nasty random variable.
Capital F of little x is a CDF.
That's just a function of real numbers,
but capital F of capital X
is a nasty random variable.
But, we don't have any problems with that.
It's just some random variable.
If I plug capital X into it's own CDF,
amazingly, I get a uniform distribution.
That's what this theorem says.
Here's the proof and I'll
just do this very quickly.
We're gonna see the proof again,
so don't worry about it
if these steps are scary.
We'll let capital Y equal
Capital F of capital X,
so it's just a nasty function of X.
Then the CDF of Y is,
let's do as little thought as possible,
the probability that Y is less than
or equal to little Y,
that is by definition.
Now, I'm lazy. I don't
know nothing about Y.
So, let's plug in what Y equals;
capital F of capital X.
That's all that we've done here.
Now, I only know about X,
so what I'm gonna do is,
I'll take the inverse of both sides.
So, in this step right here,
I take capital F inverse
of capital F on both sides;
the F inverse of both sides
gives me the next step.
Probability that X is less than
or equal to F inverse of Y.
Where did the capital F go?
Well, when I did the inverse of F times F,
I got a cancellation, and so,
that's why I'm left
with a plain old X then.
Alright, well, this is
gonna happen a second time.
Let's do the probability that X
is less than or equal
to the F inverse of Y.
By definition, that's
capital F of F inverse of Y.
The F and the F inverse
cancel again and I get Y.
If I take the derivative,
just like before,
I get the uniform distribution.
So, that's the proof.
Very, very ,very nice.
And, we're gonna encounter this
a couple other times very soon.
It's just tremendously important
to generating random
variables during a simulation.
Let's do a simple example now,
to show how to generate random variables.
In particular, the
exponential distribution.
I'm gonna use the Inverse
Transform Theorem to do this.
So, let's start out real easy.
Let's suppose that X is exponential,
and we know from a previous lesson,
that the CDF is capital F of little X
that equals one minus
E to the minus Lambda X
for X greater than or equal to zero.
So, now, I'm gonna use the
Inverse Transform Theorem.
I plus in capital X into it's own CDF,
capital F of capital X equals
one minus E to the minus Lambda capital X.
The Inverse Transform Theorem says that,
that thing, messy as
it may be, is uniform.
Thank you Inverse Transform Theorem.
Since it's uniform,
let's set it equal to U.
And, supposing I can generate
a uniform from Excel or some place.
So, set capital F of X
equal to U and solve for X.
So that's, I'm gonna take the inverse,
sort of, I'm gonna solve for X.
After a little bit of algebra,
and we'll step throughs
later on step by step.
After a little bit of algebra,
X equals negative one over Lambda
natural log of one minus U.
And so, since X started
out as exponential,
that means that negative one over Lambda
natural log of one minus
U is, itself, exponential.
So, if you can give me a uniform,
I can give you an exponential.
It's brilliant!
So, for instance, if Lambda equals two
and U equals .27, I plug
in Lambda equals two,
U equals .27 right there
and I get X equals .157.
That's my exponential to random variant
or realization, as they call it.
Here's another example.
This is the Weibull distribution.
I'm gonna just walk you
through this very quickly.
Suppose X, as the Weibull distribution,
turns out that mess is the CDF.
One minus E to the minus Lambda X,
all that raised to the Beta power.
The Weibull distribution is
a complicated distribution
used in reliability theory and you can see
that if I set Beta equals one,
the exponential is
actually a special case.
So, if I set capital F of X equal to U,
just like before, and
solve for X, you can show,
do this during the commercials tonight,
that X equals one over Lambda
minus natural log one minus U,
all that raised to the
one over Beta power.
You can do that yourself.
That's like a little exercise for you.
And, what I'd like you to do,
if you have a little extra time,
I'll make this an
assignment at some point.
Pick your favorite
values of Lambda and Beta
and generate a bunch of X's.
You can then make a histogram
and you've got yourself
a Weibull distribution.
One nice thing is to
look at different values
of Lambda and Beta and see
what the thing looks like.
It turns out that, if
Beta is less that one
or if Beta is greater than one,
the thing looks very
interesting in comparison.
I'm gonna do a quick bonus here.
I'm gonna walk us through
this very, very quickly
because it's already been a tough lesson,
but if you are really,
really stout of heart,
let's look at this bonus result.
And, I'm not really gonna
hold you responsible,
but I'd like you to see it.
In fact, if you don't wanna look at it,
go ahead, go to the summary,
but if you've got a couple
minutes, take a look.
This is just another way to get the PDF
of Y equals H of X for some very nice,
continuous function of H.
This looks a little like LOTUS
and we'll be talking about
LOTUS on the next page.
So, here's another way to get the PDF
of capital Y equals H of X.
For continuous function, it avoids
getting a step or two.
It looks a little more complicated,
but, it turns out, it's kinda more direct.
I'll just step you
through this very quickly.
The CDF of Y is, by definition,
the probability that Y is
less than or equal to Y.
I'm lazy, so I plug in Y equals H of X
and then I take the inverse of both sides.
If Y is nice and continuous,
I can take the inverse
and that gives me the probability that
X is less than or equal to H inverse of Y.
By the chain rule, and since the PDF
has to be greater than zero,
I take the derivative of
this thing, right there.
Little F of Y is the PDF of Y.
I take the derivative of the CDF and,
now, I use the chain rule;
X equals H inverse of Y.
Here's the derivative from the chain rule,
looking awful, but that's what it is.
The fact that the PDF is positive
means that I take the
absolute value of that term.
So, I'll use this result to prove LOTUS.
So, here's the expected value of Y,
remember, Y equals H of X,
that's what LOTUS is
the expected value of Y.
This equals, by definition,
so I haven't evoked LOTUS.
I'm gonna prove it here.
By definition, this is the integral over
the real line of Y times the PDF of Y.
That's this step right here.
I plug in, using the chain rule,
an expression from the previous page,
that awful mess from the last page.
That's what that mess is.
And, now, if you're willing to believe
that the absolute value
mess times the D of Y
is merely expressed as
D of H inverse of Y.
And, it kind of makes sense
because the DY's cancel
in the previous line.
And then, I set X equal to
H inverse of Y.
You get this result,
which is, in fact, LOTUS.
Absolutley amazing!
Here's a summary of what we just did.
This is a long, difficult lesson,
but we got through it just fine.
We looked at distributions of
functions of random variables.
And, perhaps, the most
important thing for this class,
is that along the way we used
the Inverse Transform Theorem
to turn uniforms, magically,
into arbitrary distributions.
We looked at the exponential and Weibull.
You give me a uniform, I'll give you
any distribution you want.
And this is extremely useful
in simulation all the time.
So, next time, if you
liked one random variable,
you're gonna love two.
We'll generalize a lot of
the results that we've done
over the last couple lessons
into bi-variant distributions.
Random variables with two components.
So, looking forward to that,
We'll see you next time.
(bell chiming)