- In this lesson, I'm
going to be solving certain
nonlinear equations, looking for zeros
in all the wrong places.
So, here's the lesson overview.
Last time, I talked about
certain calculus basics,
and right at the end, we
started looking for solutions
to nonlinear equations, in
other words, finding a zero.
This time, I'm going to be
a little bit more formal
about ways that we can
conduct such a search.
The material is going
to be used several times
in the course, take my word for this,
because it's actually
very, very important,
and is useful in a lot of
different methodologies
within simulation.
So, finding zeros, how
might you find a zero
for some complicated linear function?
In other words, I'm
looking for the value of x,
such that f(x) = 0.
There's a couple ways:
trial and error, now
I've used this before,
it is not so great, sort of a
search and destroy type thing.
Bisection, this is actually better.
Here we're using a sort of
divide and conquer strategy,
where we at least narrow things
down every step of the way,
and Newton's method, or some
variation of Newton's method,
this is sort of a highly
dependable, very quick method,
and then, maybe later on in the course,
we may have time to look
at a fixed-point method,
those are a little bit more
complicated and specialized,
but they're very nice as well.
So, here's an example that you may recall
from the last lesson, and
this example actually has
an exact answer, at least
we can solve for it.
Nevertheless, I'm just going to remind us
of this example just for
stabilization purposes.
Let's find the value of x
that minimizes this function,
e to the 2x plus e to the -x.
It turns out that this
minimum can only occur
when you take the derivative
and set it equal to zero,
so I took the derivative
using the chain rule,
and I got two times e to
the 2x, minus e to the -x,
set that equal to zero.
I'm going to make a little
algebra manipulation here,
and it turns out that the solution to this
is x naught equals
negative 1/3 log of two,
and that's approximately
equal to minus .231.
It turns out it's also easy to show
that the second derivative
is greater than zero
for all x, and so since that's
concave up at that point,
x naught is indeed a minimum.
So that's actually getting a real answer,
and the thing works,
it's possible to do that.
Now we'll look at the method of bisection.
Here, let's suppose that
I can find x values,
x1 and x2, such that the function
g(x1) is less than zero,
and g(x) value of x2,
is greater than zero.
I'm using g here instead
of f because I can use
any letter I want, and
I'll follow a similar logic
if the inequalities are reversed,
but let's just pretend that
g(x1) is less than zero,
g(x2) is greater than zero,
then by what's known as
the Intermediate Value Theorem,
which you may remember
from calculus class,
if one value of x gives
you a g(x) less than zero,
and one value of x gives you
a g(x) greater than zero,
that that means that there must be a zero
in between x1 and x2,
so x*, let's say that's the zero,
falls between x1 and x2, that's what
the Intermediate Value Theorem says,
at least if g(x) is continuous.
So what I'm going to do is,
I'm now going to kind of
split things in the middle.
Let's take x3 equal to x1 + x2 over two,
if g(x3) is less than zero,
then that means that there's
a zero between x3 and x2,
otherwise if g(x3) is greater than zero,
there must be a zero in x1 to x3.
That just follows again by the
Intermediate Value Theorem.
Either way, the length of
the search interval decreases
by a factor of two, so what we'll do
is that we'll continue
in the same exact manner
until the length of the search interval
is as small as desired,
because every time we iterate
when we go to x4, x5, dot dot dot,
the length of the interval gets smaller
and smaller and smaller,
so let's try this out
for this function g(x)
equals x squared minus two.
Now, in fact, we know that
x equals square root of two
is a solution to this, so x
squared minus two equals zero,
that has a zero at x
equals square root of two,
so we know that, but by
doing this iteration,
which I'll show you on the next slide,
we'll be able to approximate
square root of two.
Now, I'll illustrate the bisection method
on the function g(x)
equals x squared minus two,
and we already know that
the zero is going to be
x equals square root of two.
I have graciously graphed
out the function in Excel,
here it is right there, beautiful.
You can see just by looking at the thing
that the zero occurs right there,
and if you look carefully, it
occurs between 1.38 and 1.44,
which is not a surprise
because you and I know
that the square root of
two is 1.41 blah blah blah.
Let's just arbitrarily
pick a starting point,
x1 equals one, and x2 equals two,
so here's x1 equals one,
x2 equals two right there,
and you can see that the g of one value
and the g of two value
are negative and positive,
and so that means, since g(x1) is negative
and g(x2) is positive, that
means that there's a zero
between one and two, so my rules says
that I split the difference
between one and two,
I take the midpoint, so x3 is going to be
x1 plus x2 over two, that's 1.5,
and here's 1.5 on the graph.
You can see that we're
getting pretty close
to 1.414,
but g of 1.5 turns out to be
0.25, which is greater than zero,
and the implication is that the zero
is between one and 1.5,
so now I can continue
in this manner, dot dot dot.
I'll calculate x4 equals 1.25,
continuing, x5 equals 1.375,
and x6 equals 1.375,
and look at this, we
can really see quickly
that x* is starting to converge,
it's converging to 1.414, kind of fast.
It's still taking its time
compared to Newton's method,
which I'll show you in a minute,
but it's doing a really good job.
So now, let's look at Newton's method.
So suppose somehow that I can
find a reasonable first guess
for the zero, say xi or x naught.
We'll start the iteration
at x, at i equals zero.
So, if g(x) has a very nice,
well-behaved derivative,
and by well-behaved I don't
want it to be too flat
near the zero, I'll show
you why in a minute,
then I'm going to
iterate my guess x sub i,
to xi plus one, as follows.
Xi plus one, my new guess for the zero,
is equal to xi
minus g(xi), divided by g prime of xi.
So, g(xi), if I'm close to my answer,
that's going to be approximately zero,
so I'm not going to be
moving my answer too much,
and depending on the derivative,
if the derivative is close to zero,
I may have to move things a lot.
If the derivative is
quite big or quite small,
or quite big negatively, I
won't be moving much at all.
But these two things taken together,
the g(x) and the g prime of x, show me
how much I'm going to be moving my guess.
Now, what I'll do if things go well,
believe it or not, is
I iterate xi plus one,
xi plus two, dot dot dot.
Things are gonna actually
converge, unless I've got
a couple crazy cases which I
won't talk about right now.
In fact, this makes sense
because if xi and xi plus one
are close to each other
and close to the zero, x*,
if you do a little bit of algebra,
you end up with g prime of x sub i,
approximately equal to g(x*) minus g(xi),
over x* minus xi, so that's
kind of the derivative
at point x sub i, so in
fact, if things go well,
this will converge fairly quickly.
Let's try Newton out for the same example
that we used for bisection,
namely g(x) equals x squared minus two,
and of course we secretly know
that the zero for this thing
is x equals square root of
two, which is about 1.414.
Notice that the iteration step
here is to set xi plus one
equal to xi minus g(xi)
over g prime of xi,
it's this thing right there, and g(xi)
is equal to xi squared minus two,
g prime of xi, is equal
to 2xi, that's very easy.
A little algebra gives
us that last expression,
xi over two, plus one
over xi, very very simple.
Let's start with this bad
guess of x1 equals one,
or x0 equals one, doesn't matter.
Here's what we have, x2
equals xi over two,
plus one over xi, and
xi is x1 in this case,
so x1 equals one, so that's one over two,
plus one over one, which is equal to 1.5.
Now, I plug 1.5 into this equation,
1.5 over two, plus one over 1.5,
now we get 1.4167.
Actually, it's a bunch of sixes,
but I rounded up to six seven.
Then finally, I plug 1.4167
into here and here,
and I end up with, on just
three or four iterations,
1.4142, amazing, very
close to the actual answer,
1.414 blah blah blah, and it
only took three iterations.
Absolutely fantastic, very very nice.
Here's a summary of what we just did.
I went over some very easy,
basic techniques to solve
certain nonlinear equations for zeros.
Next time I'll be doing the
battle of Leibniz versus Newton.
It's going to be integration
time, we're going to see
a lot of old friends from calculus class.
I hope everybody is looking
forward to that, because I am.
(mysterious music)