Well now we're gonna look at the Seize,
Delay, Release,
actually just the Seize Release example,
as our demo to introduce
the Advanced Process template.
This is short and sweet,
very straightforward, very easy.
What I'm gonna do here,
is I'm gonna use separate Seize and
Release blocks to do overlapping
seizes and releases.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, let's just take a look here.
Let's run the thing for a second.
I've set this up, and
you can have access to that.
So a bunch of customers here, and they're
lining up at this Process, getting served.
Not sure if it's a barber shop or
whatever, I'll look into it in a minute.
But look at this.
It doesn't seem that there's ever
a line forming at this Process.
And why is that?
Well, here's what I'm doing.
I've got a line forming in front of this
Process, where I do a Seize and Delay.
And then this Seize is for that Process.
This Release is for that Process.
So a customer can't go through and
therefore cannot release the server until
a slot is ready over
here in Process number 2.
That's why no alliance forming over here,
all the line gets pushed
back over to this guy.
There is no line now, but if there
was a line it's gonna be over here.
So lets see exactly what I did.
This is very short and sweet like I said.
Create the customer in the usual way.
Seize, Delay, Release, so for
Seize Delay, there's no Release here.
For once it's not a barber, Resource 1.
So I just do Seize Delay.
This is a Seize block that I got
from the Advanced Process template.
Seize and just dragged it over.
It comes with its own queue.
But since there is no queue,
you don't see one appear here or here.
Then in this release,
I release Resource 1.
And now in Process 2,
I've already seized it at this point.
I do Delay Release and
all the customers go off hap hap happy.
So again,
I'll show it to you one more time.
There you go, see?
All the queue is relegated to this area.
Now, one thing I promised
to do is show you,
remind you how you get
the Advanced Process template.
It may be easier for you than for me.
But I always go to File >
Template Panel > Attach.
And then you start looking around, and
since the last time I looked around,
I actually got to the Template Panel.
Eventually it remembered that and
here I am.
So look at all these things I could get.
I'm just gonna get the AdvancedProcess,
which I clicked on that's why I
have the panel sitting to my left.
And I could also got AdvancedTransfer,
BasicProcess, which is,
we already have blocks which you'll
see a couple of lessons from now, etc,
etc, very very nice.