In this demo, I'm gonna show you
the use of certain primitive blocks.
In particular the queue block,
the seize block, and the delay block.
So let me show you here.
Blocks, I previously loaded that template,
and I go around, I look,
they're in alphabetical order, so if I
want a delay block, bang, there it is,
I can just drag it over.
I don't want it, so let me Delete it.
And we're gonna be seeing pretty much
the same example again when we do
the call center example later on, and so
I'm not gonna go into huge detail here
other than to say, I create some arrivals.
I'm gonna try to seize this resource.
The resource is called Trunk Line.
It's just the number of
telephone lines that I have.
And if I remember correctly,
let's go to Basic Process > Resource,
I have a Trunk Line that
has a Capacity of 3.
So I have three Trunk Lines, in other
words, three phone lines are available.
I'm willing to put up with
a queue of size 4, so
this is where the queue is defined,
trunkline.queue.
So if I go over here,
this is a first in first out queue and
the Capacity of this queue is 4.
If I use a queue block, which is
the main reason I use a queue block.
If I exceed the capacity of
the queue I automatically kill
off the customers by sending
them to this dispose.
So that's what is nice about the queue
block, that's why people use it.
If the queue block is overcapacitated,
out you go.
So the only way I can use a seize block
with this particular queue block is that
I've got to use the primitive seize block.
That's why I'm not using the yellow
one from the advanced process or
the process version of the seize, so
I'm stuck with this primitive seize.
And then I'm stuck with a primitive delay.
So I just want to show you what's
going on here, this is not a big deal,
cuz we'll be seeing this again later on.
These numbers here represent
the number of people in the queue, and
the number of servers being used.
One thing being queued here is
that I have a three way by chance.
And so the customers will go to
the first choice with probability 76,
just like the number of trombones in
the big parade, with probably 16%
to the second choice and was remaining
probably 8% to the third choice.
So let's watch,
I'm gonna step through this, here we go.
Click, first customer shows up.
There's nobody in the queue right now,
so he goes through,
there's nobody seized at this point.
One server is now being used.
Second guy shows up,
two servers are being used.
Third guy shows up,
three servers are being used.
Fourth guy shows up,
one person in the line.
See how that works?
We also had somebody leave and so
that fourth guy is now being served.
So you can see how this works.
It's very nice.
Let's run this sorta slowly and we'll
see how the queue builds up and down.
There we go, see, we had a queue
of four so a guy had to leave.
We will see that again.
See, when the queue gets to be four,
customers have to leave.
Isn't that nice?
Very, very easy example.
And you can see how the blocks work so
nicely.
Like I said, we'll be going into
much more detail on that later on.
Okay so let me now do a very cute
little example that I worked up.
This is using an alter block.
This is the block, this is alter.
Now where is he?
In alphabetical order, I drag this guy
over, alter, and what the alter block
does, he's responsible for adding servers
to a resource, or subtracting servers.
So let's look at this one.
It says Barber 1.
What that is doing is if you
pass a customer through here,
or a fake customer, the number of
servers in the barber increases by 1.
And f I wanted to,
I could put a 2 here or a negative 1.
I could change the number of
servers by anything I want, but
alter is used to change the number
of servers that are resource.
Sometimes I say number of resources, but
I really mean number of servers that
are resource, number of parallel servers.
So let's watch.
Here's the Create block,
this Decide block is just saying,
if the number of people in the queue is
greater than or equal to 3, add a server.
And we can keep track of the number
of people in the queue and
the number of resources being used.
Let me actually just see how
many people are in this barber.
So we currently have, in the barber,
I'm going to look at the number resources.
So the barber has a capacity of 1.
There's a Trunk Line which
we're not using anymore so
you can ignore that,
in fact I'll just Delete it.
Out you go, okay.
So we're keeping track of the number
of barbers that we have in use and
the number of people in line.
We'll step through this.
Okay so first guy shows up,
there's only one guy,
he's not waiting for
anybody, so there he goes.
Not the fastest guy ever.
So one person's being used.
Next guy shows up, we still don't
have a queue bigger than three.
I got to speed these guys up.
So there's only one server so
the queue size is one now.
Next guy shows up,
queue size is going to bump up to two.
let's see what happens to the queue size.
That's interesting.
Now three, I needed to click,
another guy shows up.
Now, something is gonna happen here.
The queue is greater or equal to three so
we go through an alter block and
now we have two servers,
see what happened?
We have two servers because we
went through the alter block.
And the queue went down to two.
The guy showed up, so
then it popped back up to three.
Let me see if we have another server here.
The queue is three,
we're gonna add another server.
See look at that,
now we have three servers.
And you can see this is quite nice.
We're gonna keep on adding
servers until everybody's happy.
There's another one.
See, so we can run the simulation for
awhile.
And you'll see that occasionally,
the number of servers will go up.
By the way,
NR means the number of servers in use.
So we'll see, it's won't go above
four until we really need it.
And let's see if that ever does.
Well, looks like four is
probably what we needed.
So we're not getting these gigantic lines.
So four is probably a very good number for
the system.
Okay well,
this is a good place to end the demo.
Don't want to have you waiting around,
else the queue size will go up.
So we'll see you in the next lesson.