In this demo, I'm just gonna show you how
to use failures, and we'll take a look and
see that they actually work.
Failures working is kind of fun.
So this is the old example
out of the Arena book,
model 3-1, and what I've done
is I've added in some failures.
So this drilling center is gonna have
a failure every once in a while.
So let's take a look at the resource.
This resource is called drill press.
It has a fixed capacity of one,
and I had a failure scheduled.
So what I did, I clicked in here,
I've got one row worth of failure,
it's called drill failure,
what a surprise, I named it that,
and the failure rule is in ignore,
doesn't matter for now.
So, what did I say to do?
We click in there, and
then we go to advance process.
And we look at the failure spreadsheet.
There it is, right there.
And we see that I have a drill failure,
and
I've defined it as a count type failure.
So after ten customers come in,
we fail and we have a down time,
expo 30 that's nice, Expo(30).
And so the system will fail for
about 30 minutes, and
then come back on, we'll get 10 more
customers, and then another failure.
One thing that's interesting
is clicking into this graphic,
we'll see that something's gonna happen.
It's gonna disappear
when a failure occurs.
Let me get out here, let's click OK.
All right, so here we go.
I think what I'll do is
I'm gonna step through so
you can see one customer.
Two, three,
four.
I think we're on our fifth now,
sixth, seventh, eighth.
Ninth, and I think the tenth is coming up.
There's ten, and look what happened, gone.
So we're experiencing a failure now,
let's run it a little bit longer and
we'll see what happens.
Yeah, failure, failure, failure.
The queue's getting bigger,
it's just terrible.
Now he's back, and
the queue is building down a little bit.
A little bit, fails again.
So obviously we're gonna have,
now simulation's over.
It was a very quick one.
So you can see that the failure
really does occur and
it negatively impacts the queue.
Easy demo, we'll see in the next lesson.