Now that we've done this call center demo,
I'm gonna do a few additional
specialty demos, and we'll describe
them in a little bit of detail as we go.
You'll see kinda the wide range
of things that Arena can do.
Here's the overview.
Last lesson,
we did that call center simulation demo.
This time, I'll give a plain English
description of a simple inventory system,
an (s,S) inventory model, and a demo.
In the next few lessons, well, we'll look
at several demos like I just promised.
Inventory model for now.
A quickie little demo on whether you
should use one line versus two lines.
What's called a re-entrant queue,
that's a lot of fun.
Things called SMARTS files and
other Rockwell demos,
these are all Rockwell things.
And then a manufacturing
system with transporters,
conveyors, and various forms of movement.
Here's a description of the (s,S)
inventory policy that we'll be looking at
in the current demo.
I'm gonna simulate the widget
inventory of some stock over time.
And we'll be using modules from
the Basic and Advanced panels.
Customer arrivals, a form of Poisson
process, Exponential 0.1 interarrivals.
So we have about ten arrivals
per day of customers.
The demand size uses the DISC function,
which we've mentioned once or
twice before.
That's a discreet distribution.
I'll mention what it
is when we look at it.
Demand is always quote unquote met.
So even if you don't have stock,
we backlog so eventually it's met.
You never send a guy away angry.
Inventory is taken, or evaluated,
at the start of each day.
You only notice that you're understocked
at the beginning of each day.
If you run out of stock, too bad.
You just backlog, backlog, backlog.
If inventory is below s, we order up to S,
that's the (s,S) inventory policy.
If s is 5 and S is 20, and
you end up with an inventory of 4
at the beginning of the day,
you order 16 that day.
The delivery lead time is
a uniform distribution,
takes more then half a day but less
then a full day before an order arrives.
It's pretty quick, but
by the time the order arrives
other customers will have also
arrived depleting inventory further.
That's an issue.
There are order costs like
set up costs for an order.
Incremental cost,
the more you order the more it costs.
Holding costs, if you've got stuff in
stock it costs you money to hold it.
And penalty costs, just because
orders are all eventually filled
doesn't mean that you don't pay
a penalty for having to backlog.
Maybe customers noticed that you didn't
have it in stock and they're ticked off.
Now what we'll do is that using all these
various costs, we wanna automatically
calculate average total cost
per day over a 120 day period.
And I'll show you how we set that up.
This is gonna involve some statistics
that you'll have to figure out how to use
yourself.
But I'll show you where that's contained.
Inventory, unit costs,
like how much does it cost to order, and
things like that, these, and
all other parameters, are variables.
So I'll show you the list of variables.
Inventory is decremented by demands,
incremented by received orders.
So demand comes in,
we decrement inventory.
When we receive an order, after
the lead time, we increment inventory.
Interarrival times, demands, lead times,
these are all expressions that we get
from the Advanced Process template.
Expressions come from advanced processes.
It's a little piece of
trivia that I always forget.
Accumulated costs are calculated
in the Statistic spreadsheet
that's located in
the Advanced Process panel.
So it's a spreadsheet
in the Advanced panel.
Daily inventory review is conducted by a
fake customer at the beginning of the day.
In this lesson, we took a little time
to discuss the (s,S) inventory policy.
Not the most complicated one,
but certainly an interesting one.
In the next lesson,
I'll look at that old Dr.
Seuss demo, One Line,
Two Lines, Red Line, Blue Line.
[SOUND]