What we'll be doing here, is we'll look
at an arrival rate that varies via
an expression, and actually a variable
that depends on the day of the week.
So here we have, I'm gonna create
some customers, and the arrival
rate is gonna depend on this expression.
One per day of week, and this day of
week rate is defined as a variable.
So let's take a look at that.
Day rate of day.
So Tuesdays are different than Wednesdays,
let's say.
So we go into basic process,
variable and look at this.
We have day, which can be,
that's just the day of the week.
We'll start out at 1.
Day rate 7 rows corresponding
to different rates per day.
How do we know what day it is?
Well, very simple.
We use this fake observation right
here to generate the days of the week.
Let's just watch.
It goes round and
round every once in a while.
Watch this.
See?
Customer comes around, 2.
He's gonna come around again, 3.
So, once a day this updates,
and this is kind of smart.
It goes 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
Then it's smart enough to come back to 1.
You can take a look at that.
And here, the rate just changes by looking
up what value in
the variable vector to take.
Does it take the first, second, third,
fourth, fifth, sixth or seventh.
So very, very simple and
this is just one little tutorial that
a reading gives you in the smarts file.
Another thing that Rockwell
is very good about,
is that it has a lot of cool little demos.
I'll show you one, for instance.
Let's look at a emergency room.
And this is a professionally
prepared demo from Rockwell.
You'll see mostly the graphics and
not the underlying logic to the thing,
but here are the graphics.
Let's watch.
It's beautiful.
If I make this a little bit fuller screen.
Quite nice, so you can see customers
coming in, the clock changes.
It's quite nice.
And this is prepared by Rockwell, and
they have numerous demos
that you can show people.
Very nice.
They come into the emergency room,
get served, there's a waiting area.
It's quite nice and it keeps track of
ongoing conditions in neutralization, and
things like that.
So, there you go.