Now we're gonna be demoing this
one line versus two line problem.
On the top here, I'll actually run it,
I've got one line feeding
into two parallel servers.
On the bottom,
I split the customers evenly,
50/50, into two separate servers.
So let's watch customers arrive here,
I can zoom in, you can see the little,
marbles coming in, the blue marbles.
Parts arrive to the system, I assign
a server time to them right away, so
wherever they go, they're going
to have the same service time.
They're gonna have
the same arrival time so
these are the same exact customers that
I split into two identical clones.
So this is a separate duplicate original,
Duplicate original and these are clones.
One clone goes up here into the single
line feeding into two parallel servers,
the other clone goes here and this
decide block mainly it's a 50/50 side,
splits into the two parallel servers.
The single drilling center up here is
a resource center with capacity two.
So basically the only difference
is capacity two, single line,
two separate lines,
each of which go into server capacity one.
So the only things I care about now
are the average number in the queues,
so looks like so far I've got 1.23
customers average number in this queue,
and looks like 0.11 here, 2.116 here.
So in this system I've got
2.3 as opposed to 1.6,
little hard to see these numbers,
and the cycle times for
option A are 16 cycle time for
option B are 21.
But what's going on is that
this simulation is very,
very early it's only 166 minutes.
Let's run it more quickly I'm zooming here
now we're at a 1000
minutes now 3,000 minutes.
And you can see, these queues on average,
average number in
queue's about 7 when you add them up,
only about 2 when you add them up here.
And the cycle times down in option B are
twice as much as the cycle times up here.
Let's run this thing to completion.
I think I run it for some 100,000 minutes,
some huge number of minutes.
On it goes, I'll stall, stall,
stall, I think it goes to 100,000.
We're at 60,000, 70,000, 80,000,
and let's see what we get.
It goes even further than that,
so I'm gonna,
what I'll do is I'll run it in batch mode.
So Run Control > Batch, Run it.
And whatever the number was,
it was quite a long time and
let's see some of the output here.
So, you can see that,
We have just as huge number of runs,
and each drilling center
had a drilling center one,
these are the two separate guys,
this is the drilling center one,
drilling center two
the two single servers and
single drilling center
is the double server.
So they have about the same number,
And these are the number in and out.
So the statistics I'm interested
in are the waiting times and
single drilling center this
is with two parallel servers,
41 minutes that's
the average waiting time.
And the two single
server lines option B is
almost it's even more than 200 minutes.
Unbelievable, so
there's a huge difference, and
I would definitely use
Option A just by looking at this.
Okay, you can play around with this
a little bit more if you want, but
the story is pretty clear,
option A definitely beats option B.