Hi everyone.
So it's one fish, two fish time,
where we're gonna compare one line versus
two lines in a particular queuing model.
Here's the overview.
Last lesson, I worked on a simple little
SS inventory policy example, very nice.
You can really play
around with that a lot.
In this lesson I'm gonna ask the simple
question, should we use one line feeding
into two parallel servers, or separate
lines feeding into two individual servers?
You may notice that different fast
food restaurants explore this problem.
So we'll use a very cool trick
called common random numbers to do
an apples-to-apples comparison.
Here's our game plan.
Option A: Customers show up and
they join one line in front
of two identical servers.
And they go to whichever
server is available first.
Option B: Customers randomly choose
which of two lines in front of
single servers to join.
Again, you could picture this
happening at certain food restaurants.
We're gonna compare which of A and
B is better by using
the exact same customer arrivals
thanks to a separate module.
So we're gonna use
the same exact customers.
That what allows for apples to apples
comparison, like a paired key test.
And we'll use the same exact service
times for a particular customer,
whether or not he's doing option A or B.
And we'll use an early
assign module to do that.
So again, we're using for
apples to apples comparisons,
the same exact customers arriving,
and the same exact service times.
The only thing that changes is the
discipline that they use, Option A or B.
So I'm gonna guess that
Option A is better.
Because well,
if you use Option B it may be that you
randomly choose not to use
server that has an empty line.
So almost certainly Option A is better.
So again, apples to apples comparison
using what's called Common Random Numbers.
The same arrival times and
service times, and
this is like doing a paired
t-test in statistics.
Wow, apples and pears in the same example.
This Common Random Numbers is something
that we'll explore again when we do
module 10.
Really, really nice trick in simulation.
Here's what the thing looks like.
Up here this is gonna be Option A,
here's Option B down here.
The separate block,
what that's gonna do is say, put the same
exact customer arrivals down to A and
B, and then we'll see what happens.
Here's a summary of what this lesson did.
Here we used Arena to compare two
different server configurations for
a simple queuing system.
Very, very simple.
And next time I'm gonna look at a really
crazy re-entrant queuing system.
It's not intuitive, but
it's very very cool.
Simulations actually the first way that
people use to analyze this crazy systems.
So see you then.
[SOUND]