In this demo I'm gonna
show how you use sets
with a small example involving
four different servers.
So let's just watch this for a second.
Just a simple seize delay release, and
it looks like I've got these four barbers.
And I'm gonna have the four barbers be
used in preferred order, A, B, C, D.
So A goes first, then B,
then C, then D if possible.
So just, let's watch.
They're all being used here.
And let's see,
you'll see that I'm gonna attempt to fill
in the left-most zeros
first if there's a tie.
So right now there's no tie.
There's a zero,
he gets filled in immediately.
See, when we had two zeros,
the one on the left gets filled in first.
Just watch carefully.
When the queue builds down,
we'll see some zeroes.
Eventually the queue will build down,
we hope.
Come on, let's go.
Zero, [LAUGH] it takes
a little longer than we think.
See, lots of zeroes,
left, left, left, left.
See how that works?
So these queues get handled and
the seized resources get
handled in the preferred order.
All right,
well let's look at some details here.
First of all,
I'm gonna show you how I set up the set.
Set, Barbers, and
Barbers is a set with four rows.
Let's click and see the members.
Barber A, B, C, D, as I promised.
Not very imaginative names,
but what can I say.
And now let's look at the language that
I have to use in the seize and release.
Remember they were awful looking.
So here's the seize, and what I did is I
added this line in plain English it says,
seize one guy from the set called Barbers.
I want to seize that guy in
preferred order, A, B, C, D.
And I'm going to store whoever
I seize in the Barber Index.
And let's suppose,
I is customer number 17, C is Barber B.
When customer 17 is done,
he will release Barber B.
Okay, then we go through the delay,
just standard boring delay.
And then I release that specific guy,
click, click.
So I've added the release in
from the set called Barber 1.
From the set called Barbers,
I released one guy,
the specific member who's
stored in the Barber index.
So if you want I can look at this
more carefully by clicking Edit.
And that has it,
you can see all the letters this way.
If I wanted to I could do other releases.
You don't want to do this necessarily
because you'll release random guys.
But in this case I used a specific member.
So very nice, very easy.
I'll let you see this one more time.
This is just keeping track of which
server A, B, C, or D is being used.
And again, C goes from left to right,
we fill in the left most zeros first cuz
we wanna use A, B, C, D in that order.
Very, very simple.
You can go play along with
this model at your leisure.