[BLANK AUDIO] Now it's finally time to
do this call center example that I've
been hawking the last few lessons.
Let's just jump right into it.
The lesson overview is as follows.
In the last lesson, I mainly discussed
how to use resource sets along with
the Seize-Delay-Release capability.
And remember,
we have to be a little careful.
The reason I did that is because that's a
key component to the call center example.
You'll see that in a while, careful.
In this lesson,
I'm gonna just describe in plain English
what the call center example is.
We've been waiting for this all along.
And when we're done with this, you can
actually start being a consultant if
you want, because I think this
problem is general enough so
that you can do a wide class
of practical problems.
And I really, really mean that.
So let's start out with the call
center description in plain English.
First of all,
the program is arranged in submodels.
A submodel is just sort of a subroutine
that undertakes a specific
task in the program that would
otherwise take a lot of space.
And you'll see that submodels
save space in the screen.
This is what one looks like.
You click inside of it, and
you see all sorts of good Arena stuff.
It just saves a lot of
space on the screen.
In the various submodels,
here's what you'll do.
You'll use one submodel to create and
direct arrivals.
So how often do arrivals show up?
Calls, and where do they go?
Do they go to Tech Support,
or Sales, or whatever?
Then we have a tech support submodel,
where we handle all
the tech support calls.
So in particular,
what kind of tech support do you need?
Turns out there are gonna be three
different types of products in this model.
It also turns out that some of the tech
support calls require return calls.
So that's another submodel.
Sometimes, the guy's gotta call you
back cuz he doesn't know the answer.
We'll also have some sales calls, order
status calls, is my order ready to go?
And a time period counter, what one
half-hour period of the day is it?
We'll be using fake customers to
increment the time period counter,
we've seen that trick before.
Let's look at arrivals,
calls show up according to
a nonhomogeneous Poisson process.
So we're gonna have to schedule arrivals.
The call center accepts
calls from 8AM till 6PM.
The arrival rates change every half-hour.
Here's a table below that I sort
of plagiarized from the book.
So you can look at that table,
and you'll see that the call
frequencies change every half-hour.
And also, I'll show you in the demo
how to use the Arrival Schedule in
the Basic Process template
to type these numbers in.
So during the first half-hour period,
we'll have a rate of 20 calls per hour.
In the second half-hour period, 8:30 to 9,
the rate goes up to 35 calls per hour.
By the way,
did you notice that I said calls per hour?
A little warning sign there.
These rates are per hour even though
the time intervals are 30 minutes.
Just a little trick you have to remember.
That's Arena for you.
A few staff actually stay at
work until 7PM in order to
let those calls that came
near 6 o'clock filter out.
I do that all the time.
I call just before the call center closes,
which is stupid, but they just
don't hang up on you at 6 o'clock.
They have to patiently get you through.
So what you have to do though is, given
that there are no calls between 6 and
7, originating at least, you have
to explicitly model 0 arrivals for
those last half-hour segments
of the Arrival Schedule.
So with the phone lines,
it turns out we have 26 of them.
If you get a busy signal,
you balk and get out of there.
So a busy signals kill you off
immediately, 26 is the limit.
Now what we'll do is
we'll use a Queue block.
We actually did a demo on precisely this.
We're gonna use a Queue block with
capacity 0 to try to seize a line.
So what that does,
if the seize of these 26 lines fails.
In other words,
if 26 lines are all being used,
there ain't no place to go in the hotel,
and you check out.
So the Queue will immediately kick
you out cuz it's got a capacity of 0.
This is a nice little trick.
The Queue and the Seize both come from the
Blocks template, we did a demo on that.
And this is the only place where
you get a Queue block, and
it only connects to this kind of Seize.
We explicitly did this in an old demo,
okay?
So recall that if you use a Seize within
a Process module in the Basic Process
template and the other type of Seize
in the Advanced Process template,
you can't connect it up with
a Queue block, so too bad.
That trick only works,
a Queue block only works in this case,
with a Seize block, not a Seize module.
3 general types of calls,
they come in randomly.
We'll handle them with an N-way
by Chance Decide module.
So each customer hears a recording.
They hear the little music,
what type of call do you wanna make?
And then he makes his choice of call.
76%, like the number of trombones in
the big parade, go to Tech Support,
16 go to Sales.
It turns out there are 7 identical,
faceless vanilla Sales guys that
we'll need to schedule as a group of 7,
not on an individual basis.
And the sales calls take a Triangular
amount of time, unimportant.
And then 8% go to Order Status.
Is my order ready, basically?
You do all that all of the time
when you call up these places.
Most callers do self-service in
a Triangular amount of time.
But some callers, about 15% of
those guys going to Order Status,
need a real Sales guy for
a Triangular amount of time.
Now let's look at Tech Support.
This is the best part of the program.
There are three different
types of tech support calls.
Again, we'll handle these via by choice,
a Decide module.
These are random Decides to go
to the three different types
of Tech Support calls.
25% are for Product 1, 34% are Product 2,
41% are for Product 3.
Each customer gets a little piece of
music while they make their choice.
And all Tech Support calls require
staff for this Triangular 3, 6,
18 duration of time.
We can make each type of call require
a different amount of time, but
this is already complicated enough.
There are some call backs.
4% of Tech Support calls require
additional investigation.
So the Tech Support guy you
talk to may not be able
to handle your request right away.
And this additional investigation is
actually carried out by another group of
staff that we are not gonna worry about.
So what happens is you talk to your
server, Sammy, or Tierney, or whoever.
They can't answer your questions so
they ask their boss.
Once they ask their boss, Tierney,
or Sammy, or whoever you talk to,
is freed up to talk to other people.
They hang up on you for a while.
The boss does some work, and then they
tell the answer to Sammy, or Tierney, or
whoever you talk to, and
then they call you back.
Investigation by the boss,
who we don't care about,
takes an EXPO one hour amount of time.
And then at that point, the original
Tech Support guy gets the information from
boss, and they call the customer back
using one of the 26 phone lines, but
with high priority.
There's no busy signal.
They wait till the first one's
available and then they call you.
That return call takes
a Triangular amount of time.
Now let's talk about Tech Support.
Tech Support guys have
some interesting issues.
They all have 8 hour days,
30 minutes for lunch, and
they all have different schedules.
Every one of them has
a different schedule.
And so we'll need the Resource Schedules
spreadsheet to model these
guys on an individual basis.
They all have different product expertise.
So we'll need Sets to model this,
and we've talked about this before.
Here the preferred orders for the set and
we actually gave an example
of this in previous lesson.
Product 1 can be handled by Charity, Noah,
Molly in blue, Anna, and Sammy in red.
Product 2, Tierney, Sean, Emma,
Anna and then Sammy, again, same guys.
Product 3, Shelley, Jenny, Christie,
Molly in blue, Anna, and Sammy in red.
Molly, by the way,
turns out was a Math major in real life.
You can see the cross functionality that
we had alluded to before in the previous
lesson.
Here is the schedule of
the various Tech Support staff.
They're all listed on the left.
All the products they can handle
are listed in the Products column.
And then that mess is their schedule.
You can see every one of them has
a little lunch somewhere in there.
So here's a summary of what we did.
We're gonna do the demo
in a separate lesson.
I gave a long, tedious verbal
description of the Call Center model.
That was the only purpose of this lesson.
Next time, it's Gigantic Demo Time, and
we're gonna get to see this Arena program
finally in all of its full glory.
And you can see that we're
putting together a lot of stuff.
Everything is actually easy, and
we just have to be patient
about putting it all together.
So you'll see it's a really fun demo.
And I guarantee,
you play around with it a little bit, you
are a consultant by the time it's over.
So let's sit back, relax, and
we'll look at the demo in the next lesson.
So see you then.
[SOUND]