In this demo, I'm gonna calculate
some normal probabilities.
And the goal here is to use fake
customers, this is a demo on fake
customers, to assist me in
calculating normal probabilities
based on the successes and
failures of certain observations.
So what I'll do is I'm gonna create
a fake customer once per hour.
I'm gonna do this,
what is that number, a million times.
I'm gonna generate
a million fake customers.
I'm gonna assign an attribute
to this fake customer.
He's gonna be a normal observation,
a normal 3 1.
And I wanna know, what's the probability
that a normal 3 1 is gonna go negative.
And that's all I'm gonna
do in this example.
So, I take my normal observation that
the fake customer's generating and
to see if the normal observation
is greater than or equal to 0,
it's not negative.
So, I count it as a non-negative
observation, and off it goes,
I dispose it.
On the other hand, if it is less than 0,
right the side block over here.
I count it as a negative observation and
off it goes into this record block.
And you can see that I'm counting it
in the counter, negative observation.
So this gets incremented by one
every time a customer goes through.
This one,
the counter is not negative observations,
that counter gets incremented by one every
time a positive observation goes through.
So I generate a normal,
if it's positive it goes up here, and
the counter gets incremented.
If it's negative, it goes down here,
and that counter gets incremented.
And then we'll look at the output for
this thing.
Now since I'm paranoid,
about these awful crystal reports thing.
Let's look at the reports and
I'm gonna go,
we're into SIMAN on this one so
that's fantastic.
Okay, so here we go so, let's run it.
Okay, I had it in batch mode,
the run is over let's take a look.
Here's a report and it turns out,
out of those 1 million observations,
998,591 were positive,
and 1,409 were negative.
And it seems to me I can
divide by 1 million.
Seems to me that we've got
about a 99.86 probability.
That a normal 3-1 will be positive and
I can tell you that's the right answer.
If I went to the back of my probability
book that would be the right answer.
Congratulations, thank you Arena.
Okay, so now the next demo that
I'll do with fake customers
is I'm gonna use fake customers
to generate break downs.
So you'll see,
let me just run this very slowly.
Whenever you see a truck,
a truck is a fake, oops,
I got to stop the other one just a sec.
Let's go back here, stop that run.
Always remember to stop it.
So whenever you see a truck, that's a fake
customer, and he's gonna be a break down.
Yep, there's a break down, right
the break down's gonna occur right there.
You can see how we had a long line form.
So the truck is being,
he's in service right now.
That's why we had the long line before.
So let's do this again
a little more slowly.
We can see what happened.
I create regular customers
every half an hour.
I created a truck every ten hours,
on average.
I assign the service time
to the regular customer,
just plain old triangular distribution.
And I assign the regular
customer priority level of 2.
Keep that in mind, priority level of 2.
The truck, I have this breakdown time of
triangular, and his priority level is one.
So he's got a priority level that
the number is lower, just remember that.
Let's then, we go to this Process block,
seize delay release,
little, the server, the Barber serves you,
what we need to do actually is
put service time as an attribute.
Let's go here expression,
Let's write out service time.
I think that's two words.
We'll find out here in a minute So
what I've done,
service time is one word, let's go back.
What I've done is I've set
up the service time now,
depending on if you're a truck or
if you're a regular person I'm gonna step
through this thing slowly, op, one last
thing, that will show you the queue.
The queue in front of the barber process
one.queue, is ranked by a lowest attribute
value of priority level, so if a guy with
a priority level of one comes through,
he beats out the guy with
priority level of two.
You'll see a truck goes to the front of
the line cause he has a higher priority
level, actually it's a lower number but
higher priority.
So, let's watch this,
I'm gonna step through.
First guy comes in, he's getting served.
You can see right there,
that 0 changed to a 1.
He's now being served,
a human is being served.
A truck comes in, the truck is in line.
He's gonna get served after that human
leaves another human comes through,
human is in line behind the truck.
Another human, he's in line,
yet another human.
That makes sense because the trucks
don't show up very often.
Another truck is about to show up,
watch what happens.
Okay, couple of things happened there.
The second truck actually
showed up right here,
because the guy left in the first
truck is now in service, so
that truck entered went all
the way to the front of the line,
cause he's a truck, he can do that, and
the first truck is now being served.
So now we're gonna get a big long
line developing, unfortunately.
More humans show up, more lines,
cuz these trucks take a long time.
Now, the first truck just left,
the second one is now in service.
So there's still a big long
task ahead before these guys
can start getting served.
Just out of curiosity, let's see if I
can generate another truck and see what,
there's another truck.
And he goes to the front of the line,
isn't that awful?
So there you go, that's how the system
runs, the fake customers are trucks, and
they're essentially generating breakdowns
where these real humans can't get served.