What we'll be doing in this
lesson is talking about
the Advanced Process Template.
Here's the overview.
Last lesson, I talked about fake customers
and we explained how they can be used for
a variety of purposes including the users
of arrival of breakdown demons.
They can be used for other things, but
we'll talk about it in upcoming lessons.
In this lesson, we're gonna add to
our arsenal of vocabulary modules
by introducing the advanced
process template.
None of this is basic stuff any more.
That's UGA, University of Georgia stuff.
Now, we're gonna do advance
Georgia Tech stuff.
Advanced process template and the idea is
that we'll get lots of great new stuff,
although I don't expect you to
have to memorize everything.
You'll look at a bunch
of important things and
at least, I want you to know where they
are not necessarily what they all do.
Here's the template.
You go to File > Template Panel > Attach,
then you have to sniff around for
the Rockwell Software directory
where you can find it.
I'll show you when we do the demo.
Here's what it looks like.
I mean, to tell you the truth,
it's usually gonna appear on your
screen as a big skinny thing.
But I expanded it, so
you could see it all in one fell swoop.
You can see a bunch of modules, the yellow
things and a bunch of spreadsheets,
lots of them.
Now I've said already and
I'll say it again,
I don't expect you to memorize all these.
Maybe you should know where you
can find them in a pinch, but
we'll only look at a few of them for now.
So for the next couple lessons,
we might be interested in say, Seize,
Delay, Release modules.
There you go, Seize, Delay, Release.
You may have heard those words before and
the Expression, Failure spreadsheets.
So there's special spreadsheets for
those guys and
you've heard those words before, as well.
Expression and failure.
Seize, Delay, Release.
Now, you've heard these things.
Why do we have to use separate Seize,
Delay and
Release modules when we have
those in the process module?
Seize, Delay, Release capabilities
is already in the process module.
Why are we messing around with those
things now and kind of second identities?
Well, I agree.
They're in the process module, but
it turns out that there are often
things that are too complicated to
do in the process module alone.
It can't handle certain things that
you would want a Seize and Delay and
Release to do kind of separately.
And remember, the basic process template
is for University of Georgia people.
And so, it's suppose to be really easy.
When you wanna do more complicated stuff,
it may be the case that you have to do
Seize, Delay and Release separately.
Possibly together, but
still separately and
we'll talk about various reasons as we go.
In particular you can handle things
like Seize, Assign, Delay, Release.
So, what if you wanted to put
something in between those blocks?
Now, you can do it.
You can do non-symmetric
multiple seizes and releases.
So before when you did a Seize, delay,
Release all in one fell swoop in
the process block and
you wanted to seize multiple resources,
usually release those same
resources in the same block.
Now, you can avoid having to do stuff
like and I'll show example later.
You can also look at very
complicated seizes and
releases that might depend
on sets of servers.
Now we'll talk about
resource sets later on,
you're gonna see those in
the upcoming call center example.
But the kind of thing that I have in mind
is just not possible in a process block.
Demo time.
We're gonna talk about some of these
Seize, Delay, Release issues and
then I'm also gonna sneak in a little
bit of wisdom about the Expression
spreadsheet that you'll see.
So, we use Expressions all the time.
I'm surprised they didn't put it in
the basic process, the template.
But as long as you know where
the expression spreadsheet is,
it's in the advance process template.
There you go and
I'll talk about a couple of the things
associated with that in demo time.
The summary of what we did in this
lesson is that we talked about
the Advanced Process template.
This is gonna give us more and
more modules, and
spreadsheets to play around with.
And in the next less, in particular,
I'm gonna use the failure
spreadsheet to talk about resource
failures and maintenance.
So, do not fail to show up for that.
See you then.
[MUSIC]