In this lesson I'm gonna finally look
at sort of a non trivial two channel
manufacturing example.
So this is a step up from some of
the earlier examples that we've been doing
with arena.
Here's our overview.
In the last lesson, I looked at
different ways to do a run control,
setup type stuff.
How to implement independent replications,
run speed, reports, that kind of thing.
In this lesson I'll put
kinda everything together.
And we'll demo a two-channel
manufacturing system where we look at
some of the concepts over the last
few lessons simultaneously.
And I want you pay particular
attention in this demo coming up,
in this lesson, how we use attributes.
We're gonna use attributes
to memorize things.
Here's the story, I'm plagiarizing
this model as model 4-1 from
the Simulation with Arena book,
which you may or may not have.
I just wanna be
straightforward about this.
In this example, we have two
different types of arrival streams.
And we've looked at multiple
arrival streams before,
now I'll be a little more formal about it.
But you have type A parts and
they show up one at a time occasionally.
We have Type B parts, they occasionally
show up four at a time in little groups,
in little batches.
Type A's show up a little
more often than Type B's.
So on average,
there's sort of the same number of A's and
B's in the system and
I I've got little colored marbles.
And you'll be able to tell which is which.
Type A's feed into a Prep A server,
where I guess they get prepared.
Type B's go to a Prep B server.
And they have different service
times at these preparation places.
This is a cool thing.
The parts get processed by
the same Sealer server.
I don't know what a Sealer is, whatever
it is they get processed by the same guy.
So they start out at Prep A and
Prep B respectively but
then they both go to the same guy.
They compete for the same resource.
What makes this interesting
is that Part A's and
Part B's have different service
time distributions at the sealer.
So the sealer is gonna have to identify
which part is he dealing with.
So all parts then undergo an inspection.
If they pass, they're out of there.
If they fail the inspection,
they have to get a rework.
They go to another server,
then they get another inspection and
whether or not they pass,
they're out of there.
So they get two tries hopefully they
pass on the second try at least.
Here's the flow chart that
I stole from the book.
Part A's come in according to
an exponential distribution with a mean of
five minutes.
Part B's, they come in every EXPO 30,
but in batches of four.
So about the same arrival rate if
you looked at them individually,
but they come in Batches of 4.
Part A's go to the preparation area,
Part A Prep.
They have a triangular distribution to
the preparation time, it's not important.
Part B's go to the separate
preparation center.
They have a different triangular
distribution, and again, that's fine.
However both types of parts A and
B go to the Sealer, common Sealer.
And the Part As have
a triangular sealing time, and
Part B's have a wide distribution for
some other reason, but they're different
and the sealer needs to know that.
How's he gonna know that, I don't know.
In any case, 9% of all parts coming out of
the sealer have to get reworked if they
are so unlucky as to get reworked, that's
going to take 45 minutes on average.
And then 20% of those are totally
no good and they get scrapped.
80% are okay, they're salvaged and
they ship them out.
Back over here, the 91% that
passed the original inspection
gets shipped out, happy, happy, happy.
So the big question is how
to handle different A and
B service times at the Sealer?
How does the Sealer know?
I've got a couple of different
things that he can do.
Here's is trick one.
Let's pre assign the service
times as an attribute.
We'll call the attribute Sealer Time,
what a surprise.
Then Assign module immediately
after the customer arrives.
So the first thing that happens when
the customer arrives, no time passes.
We hit them with the assign module.
And the purpose of the assign module
is to tell him what is your upcoming
Sealer Time.
And whether he's a type A or
Type B, we give him a triangular.
Or we give him a wyble,
depending on if he's Type A, Type B.
Since it's an attribute,
each customer memorizes for
the future what his
Sealer Time is gonna be.
He doesn't forget it.
When he gets to the Sealer, he tells
the Sealer, well, I got a triangular,
I got a wyble.
And so each customer has his own
attribute that he remembers from then on.
And so we use that attribute regardless
of whether it's a type A or type B.
We know what the Sealer Time is gonna be,
even though we assigned it earlier.
I mean heck, it's our simulation.
We can do the stuff,
whatever we want, right.
It's our simulation.
This is actually sub Trick one, but
while I'm at it I'm gonna use the assigned
module to store each customers
arrival time, also as an attribute.
Because we're interested in seeing
what the cycle times are gonna be.
So we need to know when does the guy show
up, and we'll store that as an attribute.
When does the guy show up?
Now how do we know when the guy shows up?
Well, when we hit the assign block,
I'll use the arena variable TNOW,
which is the current time.
And I'll assign the arrival time
attribute to the value of TNOW.
So it's perfectly okay to
assign an attribute value,
equal to arena internal variable TNOW.
So you assign at that point.
If you showed up at time 11.7,
he always has the arrival time for
that customer as 11.7.
What we'll do is we're gonna record the
departure times just before the parts get
disposed.
We're gonna use that record block finally.
And this will allow us to get cycle times.
What we'll do is I'll take the departure
time and when he hits the record block
just before the dispose, minus the arrival
time, the arrival time attribute.
And what we're interested in is how long
do these guys stay in the system depending
on if they pass the first inspection,
pass the second inspection or
fail both inspections?
Let's get logical.
This is actually my real sudden trick.
Is there another way to model the process
time at the sealer without having
to use that assign block,
the sealer time attribute for A's and B's?
Well, there is.
It's a little bit of a hassle,
but I wanted to show you this.
It involves a little work.
It's nice to know.
This is the kind of thing
you can use later on.
Note that the entity types,
Part A and Part B,
we assign those in any case
right in the create modules.
I'll show you,
those are assigned right away.
So instead of using the Sealer Time
as an attribute in the assign module,
what I can do is, I won't do anything
until I get to the Sealer Process.
Then I'll use a logical expression.
Now logical expression reads like this,
we say that (x==y) = 1.
So what this means is does
really really equal y?
We say that this is gonna be equal
to one if in fact x does equal y.
So if I had something like (3==3),
that value (3==3
)as a logical expression is true,
and so it equals 1.
If I had (3==2), then this =0.
So that's why it says see why.
So I always interpret the double
equal sign meaning, they really,
really equal each other.
Okay, so here's the logical
statement that I'll use.
When I get to the sealer,
if the entity type is a part A I
used a triangle distribution.
If it's a part B, I used the WEIB
distribution, which is what we're doing.
Now why does this work?
Well let's see.
If entity type is part A,
this thing is equals one.
And I have one times triangular,
which is correct.
But if it's part A,
I also have this part equal to zero.
So if the entity type is really part A,
this logical expression = 0 so
the WEIB doesn't matter.
On the other hand, if entity type
is a part B, that = 0 and this = 1.
So I get the right answer.
Now it's cumbersome, but it works.
And I'll just show you how
that does when we do the demo.
So here is what the darn thing looks like.
Part A is arrive.
I do the assign of various things,
they get prepped, they get sealed,
they go through an inspection.
If they pass 91% chance, they go through
the record block and they leave.
They're shipped off very nicely,
hap, hap, happy.
If they fail the inspection,
they get reworked, another inspection,
out they go for better or for worse.
Part B's, same thing, they get created,
they get these various assignments that
we'll talk about like the sealer time.
They get prepped, go to the sealer,
inspection, out of here one way or
the other.
So here we go demo time, take a look and
you'll get details on what's
going on in simulation.
Here's a summary of what
we did in this lesson.
This time, we sort of looked
at our first real system.
This was a small manufacturing system.
And I tossed in a couple nice little
tricks involving attributes and
certain types of logic.
Next time,
we're gonna look at fake customers.
These are additional ways that you
can do some cool little tricks and
we'll put them in our bag so
we can use them later on.
So this is a very interesting concept,
and I'll see you then in the next lesson.
[MUSIC]