This is the inventory policy demo,
using the SS inventory method that
we talked about in the lesson.
Let's kind of watch it.
You can see all these things.
These are all arrivals
occurring right here,
these things going through the system.
The arrivals, if I zoom in,
these are arrivals of customers.
They show up about ten times a day.
Let's see, the interarrival time
distribution turns out to be EXPO(0.1).
I'll show you that in a minute.
We decrease inventory by a discreet
amount of the order, and
then the customer leaves.
That's all that's going on.
I don't care about servers or anything
here, all I care about is inventory.
And let's, we can watch this over here.
This is called an inventory
level field bar
which you can grab from
the template up here.
This is a graph of inventory level, blue
means in the black, red means in the red.
This is back logged inventory.
This is displaying the familiar saw
tooth function that you would see
using a standard SS inventory policy.
If I zoom in, you can see inventory
goes down, down, down, down, down.
Sometimes in the red, then it jumps
up when an order is received.
When it goes below little s, which I
forget what it is here we order and
the next day, inventory shows up and
it jumps up and down, down, down, down,
down, up, up, up.
Okay, see how that works.
Whatever we're doing here,
we're not going in the red very often.
Okay, so let's now, we'll zoom back
out and I'll show you what I'm doing.
These customers come in according
to an interarrival distribution,
as I promised, interdemand time.
Turns out that's gonna be exponential,
that's an expression which
I'll show you in a minute.
We decrease inventory by the inventory
level equals the inventory
level minus the demand size.
Demand size is also an expression,
which I'll show you in a minute.
Inventory level is a variable
because it's global.
If you decrease inventory here,
you decrease it everywhere.
Once a day, I use a fake customer,
evaluation interval is once a day.
This is a fake customer.
His only job is to review the inventory.
See he goes through.
Didn't really do much.
It seems to be going through,
no order, no order.
Let's look and see what's going on.
Sometimes he goes up to this side.
There, right there.
We placed an order.
Let's take a look.
This decide block, ongoing that just
means the simulation's continuing.
If the order decision, if the inventory
level is less than little s,
the order decision is to place an order.
If the inventory's greater than
equal to little s, no order.
So let's scroll over,
assuming an order has been placed.
We update some costs,
these are various different costs.
This is the order quantity, big S minus
the current level, as I've described.
Now we have an ongoing order.
What I'm doing is I'm keeping track of
whether or not an order has occurred so
I don't place multiple
orders within two days.
We just do one order at a time.
That's what ongoing is doing.
Then we wait for
delivery by a delivery lag.
It's a uniform 0.5, 1.0.
I'll show you where that
expression is in a minute.
And then eventually, the delivery occurs,
thanks to the fake customer, and
we update the inventory by adding,
inventory level equals inventory
level plus the order quantity.
And we turn the ongoing into zero,
which means there are no
ongoing inventory orders.
Then, the fake customer goes away.
That is it.
That's how the thing runs.
And then, like I said, we keep track
of the inventory level up here.
There you go, inventory on hand,
that's what we're referring to as,
this is the name of the data piece.
And the expression is, this is actually,
this is the red version and
x inventory level zero, this is the
maximum of the inventory level in zero,
which produces the red
curve that you see here.
The black curve, sorry,
not the red curve, blue curve.
Get my colors straight.
See you can see the curve.
This produces the positive
part of the curve and
then there's another version that
produces the red negative version.
Okay, fantastic, so
let's look at a couple of things here.
In the Advanced Process,
I've got some expressions.
Interdemand time,
exponential as I promised.
EXPO(0.1).
Demand Size, DISC, looks like disco.
And that means discrete distribution
with probability one-sixth
equals one with 0.5 minus
one-sixth equals 2.
So these are the demands, one, two,
three, four with different
probabilities described here.
Evaluation Interval, well,
this is every 0.5 days.
That's why we're getting so
much blue, because I was
evaluating the thing all the time.
As it's doing multiple evaluations.
Let's see what happens if I
evaluate only once per day.
We have less information, and
then the delivery lag is UNIF(0.5,10).
So I have just changed the evaluation
period to be more pessimistic in a sense.
And then we have a number of variables and
a basic process.
Inventory level, little s,
big S, total ordering,
setup costs, incremental,
these are all variables.
How many days to run, 120,
you can take a look at all those.
And then the last thing I wanna show
you before looking at some output.
Advanced Process,
is we also use the statistic block,
which keeps track of various costs.
Holding costs, shortage costs, average
ordering costs, average shore costs.
I will leave it to you to figure
out how these are being calculated.
These are using internal arena commands.
See, for instance, MX is maximum.
You can look at these things.
It takes five minutes to figure them out.
Okay, so the only thing I'm gonna do now
is I'm gonna run this one more time with
my updated evaluation period, so
we're not evaluating as much.
I predict we're gonna see more red.
Let's see, yeah, we are getting a little
more red than what we saw before.
Yep, that makes sense.
More red than before because
we're not evaluating as often.
And just out of curiosity,
let's go back and
look at what little s and
big S were in the variable.
So little s equals 30, and
big S equals 60, that's very conservative.
Let's see what happens if
I change these things.
Little s equals 10 which is
really cutting it close I think.
And big S equals 30,
let's see what happens.
This will be the last change that
I make and we'll run the thing.
And I predict, yeah,
we're gonna get much more red now.
Yeah, this is a disaster.
I'm evaluating things too late,
I'm getting these gigantic reds.
Too bad, let's run it to completion,
so I'll hit the Go Fast sign.
Bang, I ran it for 600 days, not 120.
Let's look at the outputs.
And let me see,
I'll just show you where the costs incur.
If I had you look at various
different trials of this to optimize,
you would want to look at
the average total cost, $142, $143.
This is the thing that you care about.
Now I can guarantee that if you mess
around with the various variables,
you can get this down to about 115.
I guarantee that and perhaps you'll see
an exercise about that pretty soon.