Well, now the call center demo.
Finally gonna do this after all this time.
Here's the main screen for
the call center,
you can see it is arranged in submodels.
Here is where we get the submodel from.
Click on here, submodel, then you click
inside of it if you wanna start editing.
So I've already done that,
we have got the submodels here.
Time period counter,
create arrivals, tech support,
sales calls, order status calls,
return tech support calls.
Notice how they're connected up except for
this time period counter which
is an island all by itself.
No man is an island, but submodels are.
So let's click into this, we'll do this
first or by the way, see how it runs.
Okay, looks a little boring but
regenerating arrivals and they go through
some tech support, some sales,
some order status, some return calls.
What's going on in
the time period counter,
it's only job is to use fake
costumers to update the time period.
It turns out every 11 hours,
one of these fake customers is generated.
Every half hour, they go around
the circle, and they update the period.
The period is useful for
certain statistics gathering, and for
keeping track of when your
arrival rate changes,
when the resources, the servers
go on breaks, things like that.
So you can see when I get to 22,
it's gonna kill this off.
Watch what happens here,18, 19, 20, 21.
Here we go, 11 hours, 22.
And off it goes, and
a new one's generated.
Now, this clock here says,
it doesn't go to 6 PM,
because we're starting
it sort of at midnight.
And you have to pretend that midnight
corresponds to eight in the morning when
the simulation when the call
center actually opens.
Okay, it just goes round and
round generating,
this fake customers keep in track
of the variable called period.
So period is a variable that
keeps updated every half hour.
Okay, that's all I have to say there.
Now I'll go to the navigate bar.
I go back to Top Level, and
then let's go to create and direct.
We've seen this stuff before.
I did an entire demo on these blocks,
customers are created.
I'm just gonna run through here.
Let's run a little more slowly.
That doesn't appear to
be that much slower.
Customers are created,
they go through a queue of capacity 0.
We'll talk about that in a second.
They attempt to seize a trunk line,
there are 26 trunk lines.
This queue has capacity 0.
See the 0 there?
So that means,
if it can get in the seize block,
it's forced to stay over here at the queue
block, but queue block has capacity 0.
So it's kicked out over here.
It goes through a couple statistics
gathering things, don't worry about those,
and is disposed.
If it can seize the guy,
one of the trunk lines,
we assign an arrival time,
it listens to music.
And then we determine the call type,
that's what this endway by choice is,
let's take a look.
Endway by chance, I always say choice,
endway by chance.
76% goes off to product type one,
76% goes to call center.
Tech support, 16% goes to sales and
the remaining 8% goes to order status,
that's the purpose of this.
Then, it looks like we exit the submodel.
These things are provided automatically.
So we exit the submodel,
go back to navigate.
Top level and see, one, two, three.
Tech support, sales, order status.
Let's do sales right now,
it's the easiest thing.
Very simple, seize the sales guy, delay
him for awhile, Release the sales guy.
Now in fact, you're done.
So you have to release the sales guy, and
don't forget to release the trunk line.
So this is a delayed release of
the trunk line that you originally
seized back in the submodel,
where we created the arrivals.
Okay, so this is a good point now
to take a look at some resources.
Basic process, resource spreadsheet.
Let's look at these resources.
A lot of resources,
holy smokes, Charity, Noah,
Molly, these are all
the tech support guys.
We'll look at them in a minute.
They all have schedules, and
then the sales force,
it turns out they have a schedule.
There's seven of them but they have
schedules cuz they can go on lunches but
they're all vanilla and
faceless and the same.
They do have a schedule, though.
And then the trunk line is a fixed
capacity of 26 phone lines.
So we'll look at these schedules, Charity,
Noah, Molly, blah, blahm blah in a minute.
Schedules, there we go.
Here's Charity's schedule, click.
And, so she's working,
this is eight in the morning.
This looks like one, two, three,
three and a half hours, so this is 11:30.
She works for three and a half hours,
lunch break, works some more, goes home.
So that's charity.
Not gonna save her schedule.
Let's look at Noah.
Yeah, he works later in the day, so
see everyone one of them has
got a different schedule.
We don't need that noise.
Then we can look at the sales schedule.
These are the faceless sales team.
We start out with three in the morning,
goes up to seven.
They take some lunches
a couple of them sequentially.
Goes back up to 7 and
then there's 5 by time 11.
So that corresponds to 6, that's 11, so
yeah, that corresponds
to 7 PM when they leave.
Okay, and
these are in half hour increments.
Sometimes, it doesn't make sense to click
on these because you wanna get more fine
tuning, but when you have these discrete
integer increments, this is just fine.
I'll show you how to do this without
clicking on these in a second,
when we look at the arrival schedule.
So notice,
this is an arrival type schedule, so
in the type you have to click arrival.
Let's take a look at this.
Much more complicated looking, but
what this is, see we have about,
this number is,
you could look under the OK.
This is 20 arrivals per hour,
35, you can see it goes up, and
then down as the day progresses.
These last two zeros correspond to
the period between 6 and 7 o'clock
when there's still a couple staff members
around but we cut off the arrivals.
So these remaining customers filter
through the system at this point.
It's perfectly okay to click these numbers
in, but what some people like to do.
I'm gonna say no,
I'm not gonna save the changes.
You can right-click, right-click and
edit via a spreadsheet.
This is what I usually do if
I have a complicated one.
And let's do this.
See, here we've just
typed these in by hand.
Notice that when it says duration here,
this means,
we have a rate of 75 customers
per hour for two time periods.
This is two half hour time periods,
this means,
70 customers per hour for
one half hour time period.
Remember, this time periods are always,
What we define, but the 70 and
75 are always per hour.
So we define the time periods
as one-half hour time periods.
But the arrival rates
are always in per hour units.
A little confusing, but
you just have to get used to it.
So when we see this 75 for
two half hour time periods, what this is,
let's take a look at it again.
See, when we have, let's see,
where does that happen?
Right there, see, two time periods
in a row, 75 and what they're doing,
they're saving space in
that little spreadsheet.
It's a little stupid but
that's what they do.
Okay, so that's easy.
And this gives me
the various arrival rates.
Okay, now the last thing I'll look at
are the resource sets, And here they are.
We have these resource sets,
ignore these guys like I said before.
Product 1, there's Charity, Noah, Maui,
Anna, and Sammy, in preferred order.
Product 2, Tierney, Shawn,
Emma, Anna, and Sammy,
again in preferred order, so you can see
the cross functionality Anna and Sammy.
Let's go to Navigate, Top level.
And I am now gonna cruise right into
the tech support module right here,
so I can do that there.
And that's what it looks like.
What a mess, but it's actually quite easy.
So I'm zooming in, and
let's run the model.
See they come in,
they randomly choose one, two,
or three of these, are the product types.
They do a certain assignment, this is
when they actually start getting served.
So seize, when did we start
getting served, seize the server,
when they start getting served,
delay for a while,
release the server, and
the phone line and leave.
Now, there's a possibility of a call back,
we'll get into that in a second.
Okay, and so let's watch this.
We're gonna seize product 1,
assign the arrival time, delay
product one servers, and then release
product one server in the phone line.
So let's do a deeper dive there.
This, of course, is just the probability
of going to product 1, 2, or, 3.
So seize as I promised,
seize one server from the set of
product one guys, in preferred order.
Store that guy's name, the person
that you seized and tech agent index.
Let's assign the product type as one,
we'll use that later on.
The call starts at time T now.
Delay the guy for an expression called
tech time that's defined over here.
Let's see, I think it's an expression,
so we go into advanced process.
Yep, there it is, expression,
tech time, triangular 3, 6, 18.
The reason that we put as
an expression instead of just typing,
Triangular or whatever was here,
is because we use the same tech time
in three places and we wanna be lazy.
And not have to type triangular blah,
blah, blah in three places,
especially if we change it.
Okay, then when you're
done getting served,
release one guy from
the set called product 1.
Make sure it's the specific
number that you've used and
that specific number is
stored in tech agent index.
Okay, so be careful about that.
And then, of course, release the phone
line, so somebody else can use it.
A very simple, okay?
So then, let's go back to the top.
Navigate and
here's what we're looking at, whoops.
We just got done with tech support.
By the way, I can move it around like this
too, but that I always screw this up.
So we just got done with tech support, and
you'll notice that all these customers
are routed into return tech call.
See they're all going
to return tech calls.
Now only 4% of the customers actually
get a return tech support call.
Zoom in, and so
that means, that 96% of them are not
effected that happens right here.
Let's watch.
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, see,
almost everybody's going here.
What happens is that they
are immediately disposed.
So only 4% actually go to return tech
support, all the way through here.
96% of them are disposed, you can watch.
I see every once in a while, you'll
actually get one that's, there we go,
we finally got one, and
they go to the product type 1, 2, or 3.
I'm gonna just click in on these now and
go through this fairly quickly.
Remember, we set as an attribute in tech
support submodel,
what kind of product type you were?
So we do N-way by Condition,
which product type you are,
if you're product type 1, 2,
or 3, that's where you go.
This is a seize, delay, release again.
Let's see, so you have to seize
a phone line, seize trunk line,
because the guy's calling
you back with high priority.
So, the sales guy's actually
calling you back, but
it's equivalent to you calling
them back with high priority.
And not having to go through
that queue block, so
you get the first available trunk line.
So he sees that.
You also,
you don't actually seize that until your
able to seize your tech support guy first.
So you do this one,
then you get the phone line.
So seize one guy from product one, the
specific member that you talked to before,
not preferred order anymore, it's
the specific guy you talked to before.
Because you remembered who he was,
tech agent index.
You use them for a while,
return call time,
which is return tech time,
it's another expression.
And then you release that guy,
using the same command as before,
release one guy from product 1 sets,
specific member,
tech agent index, and then,
release the phone line.
You're done.
So there's one thing I forgot to show,
and I'll just do that in two seconds,
cuz it's so easy.
Order status, and
basically what that is, let's watch it.
You go through a little delay from
the order status, you're asking, well,
how's my order doing?
You do that by yourself.
And then,
some small number require a sales guy.
So all this is doing,
this looks real sloppy.
All this is doing is it's
just seizing a sales guy.
And then either way, either if you go
through the sales guy or you don't,
you end up right here and
you release the phone line.
So very, very simple, and that's it.
So what I encourage you to do,
is you may need to look at
this demo a couple of times.
There's a lot of stuff going on here, and
I went through things fairly quickly, but
look at the demo a couple of times.
Once you understand everything,
you are consultants, congratulations.
You've just done a very,
very difficult model, and
you're ready to go make
a lot of money now.
Here's a summary of what we did.
This time, I put together everything, and
we finally demoed the Call Center
example in its radiant glory.
In the next lesson,
what I'll do is describe in plain English,
an inventory system, and
then do a demo there.
We'll be doing a bunch of these
specialty demos from now on.
So see you then, can't wait.
[SOUND]