[NOISE] All operators are busy
at this time, please hold.
>> Well, now we're finally gonna do our
call center demo, and what I'll do is I'm
gonna describe a little bit of what
we can expect to see in the demo.
Lesson overview is that,
in the last lesson I described in plain
English what was going on
in the call center model.
So I just talked and talked and
talked about all the stuff that
was going on in the model.
We didn't do a demo,
that's what we're gonna do this time.
Demo time.
Now, what we've done is
that we're putting together
lots of different ideas from
many of the recent lessons.
Everything from sort of this concept
of fake customers to resource sets.
All of that takes place in this demo.
Let's be on the lookout for
the following things.
Keep an eye out for these things.
Submodels, that's that funny-looking
icon that I showed you right at
the beginning of the last lesson.
Fake customers used as timers.
We're gonna use a queue
with a capacity of 0.
This is they kick you out
of the hotel if it's full.
So we'll kick customers out if
all 26 phone lines are busy.
You don't even get a chance.
Non-Homogeneous Poisson arrivals.
Three resource sets for tech support,
each one of which has a especially
a product type one, two, or three,
and there's some cross functionality.
Tricky Seize-Delay-Releases, we've
talked about those a couple times now.
And quirky callback procedures.
Now it's demo time.
You'll be seeing the following
interesting screenshots.
This is a Top-Level View of the model
with the various submodels displayed.
This is what Tech Support looks like.
So you click into that Tech Support
Submodel up here, you click into that and
you get this mess.
This is the Time Period Counter.
Its only job is to click off 1, 2,
3, up to 22, cuz there's 22 half
hour periods in an 11 hour day, to keep
track of what period of the day is it.
And then the Arrival Submodel.
We've actually looked at a very,
very close variation of this thing before.
This is the arrivals where we
use that cube block etc, etc.