I'll be doing a demo on
this manufacturing cell.
Let me just get the darn thing running.
It's very pretty.
Yeah, let me slow down a little bit.
You can see different types of customers,
in fact let's do that setup and
make it quite a bit slower.
Run speed at a zero,
we're getting used to this by now.
See different types of customers,
blue, red and
green marbles going around the place.
They actually have different
paths that they're travelling.
The blue guys go from cell 1,
2, 3 and 4 in that order.
The red guys go, if I remember 1,
2, 4, 2, 3, in that order.
The green guys, I think, are 2, 1, 3.
But you can see they're all moving around.
They have different sequences.
And here's the code.
I'm just gonna do this in very,
very high level language.
Parts are created, we assign them their
sequence here along with their part type.
There's a blue guy.
He goes to what's called a station.
He figures out what his
sequence is gonna be.
And the blue guy's, let's wait for a blue
one, he'll go to Station 1, 2, 3 and 4,
and now there's blue.
See right there, Station 1.
He pops over,
now he's gonna go to station 2, see there.
Then he's gonna go to station 3 and
in a second he's going to go to station 4.
Let's watch for him over here.
Come on go to Station 4.
He'll show up in a second.
Come on, come on.
He really will unless there might have
been a line at Station 3, there we go.
So he goes to Station 4 and
then he's out of there.
So it's very, very nice.
And the only thing you need
is the sequence block,
use of sequences in this route block.
So route just says,
where we gonna go next?
And it says in plan
English in transfer time,
in this case this is a variable
of length two minutes.
So it takes two minutes to go to the next
place by sequence by your sequence.
That's all you need to do and
all this stuff is in the so
called advanced transfer template
which I have loaded here.
You can see this is the sequence
spreadsheet, and it's very, very nice.
If I want the route block,
I just drag it over.
Stations are just places that you go.
So you can see that it's
very easy to run this model,
take about an hour to learn how to do it,
but that's for another time.
The last thing I wanna show you then is
I can do movement involving a machine.
In this case, a transporter.
So see the little green thing there?
This is just a guy that picks you up,
like a taxi cab or a cart.
And let's run this.
He picks up a customer too, drops him
off at Cell 1, and then he's free.
And then he's not free anymore,
he's gonna go over and get the next guy.
And when they move they're not free.
I'm gonna go back here and wait for
the next guy, picks him up, drops him off.
Isn't that nice?
And if I want,
just the last thing I'll show you.
If I don't think that these
are enough transporters,
let me move these a little faster.
If I don't think that I have enough
transporters, maybe I don't.
I can go to the Advance Transfer.
Transporter spreadsheet.
Let's make four of them.
Isn't this easy?
And now rerun it.
And see now I have four transporters
moving around, so easy.
And so I'll give you a small assignment
that you can play around with this
a little bit.
You don't have to do
the programming itself though.
Okay, well that ends this
last demo of the module.
I hope you had a nice time looking at it.