Hi class.
Well, we have interesting
lesson this time.
We're gonna be talking about two of my
favorite things, set theory and joy.
So we'll see what's in store for us.
In the overview, in the last lesson
we talked about the so-called Blocks
template where we came across
all these millions and
millions of new blocks that we
could use in our simulation.
And they occasionally will help us
with specialized little issues and
we'll see a couple examples
of those coming up.
And then in this lesson we're
gonna learn what sets are and
how they enhance our modeling ability.
You'll see that there
are numerous ways to use them.
So we'll especially concentrate
on what are called resource sets.
Those are the most important things for
us right now.
Sets, as in baby math that
you learned in fourth grade,
a set is just a group of elements and
elements are allowed to
belong in more than one set.
Elements can mean anything in Arena.
So there are various types of sets.
You have a resource set.
So a resource set would
be a set of servers.
You have a counter set.
Remember in a previous demo,
I showed how to do counts of certain
things as they passed through the system.
We could have a set of these counters.
We could have a set of
what are called tallies.
We could have a set of entity types,
of entity pictures, and
even more difficult things,
which we will talk about later on.
Now resource sets in particular
are very easy to construct.
What we'll do is we'll use the Set
spreadsheet in the basic process template
to define sets.
So the Set spreadsheet is sitting there
in the basic process template, and
like I said we'll just study
resource sets for now.
Let's review what a resource is.
A resource currently, a vanilla
resource currently has identical,
interchangeable servers.
So if you have a resource that has
five barbers, they're all the same.
We don't care which is which.
We just wanna use one of them.
They're all the same to us.
A resource set though can have distinct
servers, Joe, Tom, Bill and they can
have different schedules, different
service speeds, different specialities.
So in fact a resource set is much
more general than this plain
vanilla resource that itself might
have five different servers.
A resource set that can have five distinct
servers all with different properties.
In our call center example we'll have
three products with the following
recourse.
So we'll have,
in the call center, you go and
you have a question about
one of the products and
you have to talk to one of the people
associated with the three products.
So let's see who can do what.
You have a question about product 1 you're
gonna need to talk to Charity, Noah,
Molly, Anna, or Sammy.
One of those five.
Product 2, you'll need talk to Tierney,
Sean, Emma, Anna and Sammy.
So look those last two kids appear
as they did in product one.
So you're allowed to have people
appearing in multiple sets.
And then product 3 set, you'll need to
talk to Shelley, Jenny, Christie, Molly,
Anna, and Sammy.
The reason I call them kids by the way
is that these are actually the kids of
the people who wrote the Arena book.
They're no longer kids, but
you can see that some of these
kids have cross functionality.
And you'll notice that I've listed
them at the ends of those lists,
because it turns out you can order sets,
unlike what you learned in math class,
sets can be ordered.
And what I'm doing, I'm saving
the most talented guys for last,
because you don't wanna waste
them if you don't need to.
So all 11 of these servers, by the way,
have different schedules too.
So not only do they have
different specialities,
they have different schedules
that they adhere to.
Now continuing with resource sets,
let's say I wanna define
a resource set called product 1.
What I'll do is when I get to
the spreadsheet, I choose Type = Resource,
because there is other types of sets,
so the type of this set is resource,
I click in members and I enter
Product 1 servers under Resource Name.
But here's what it looks like.
This is what the resource
spreadsheet looks like.
You can see we have numerous
types of set spreadsheet.
I have numerous types of sets,
Product 1 is a resource set.
Product 2 also a resource set.
We have a tally set.
Don't worry about these for now.
We'll just look at these resource sets.
And I chose type people to resource.
I click in members and then I just start
clicking in the members of that set.
Charity, Noah, Molly, Anna and Sammy.
Just like I listed on the previous page.
See, there's the type.
I'm gonna click into the number rows
there, and I just start typing away.
Now Product 1's Preferred Order,
all things considered,
I wanna use Charity first.
I wanna wait to use Anna and Sammy
because of their cross-functionality.
I could use those guys for
other purposes later on.
So Charity goes first.
If she's not available, I try Noah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
I saved Sammy for last,
because he's cross-functional.
And it'll turn out, by the way,
that other orders are possible.
We'll talk about that in a minute.
Now when I do a seize-delay-release of
people associated with a resource set.
So I wanna seize one of
these Product 1 workers.
I've got to be very, very, very careful.
I have to be careful because, and
there's a little your pre-warning sign.
The problem is that you have to
make sure that you release the same
exact person that you originally seized.
You just can't say seize-release
arbitrarily, cuz if you release a random
server some other customer may say hey,
where'd my server go.
So you've got to be very careful
about the person that you release.
If you seize Sammy,
you gotta release Sammy.
So here's what it looks like.
Seize-Delay-Release using the advance
process blocks, Seize-Delay-Release.
Let's suppose we seize a server from
the set Product 1 in this preferred order,
from top to bottom.
And we got to make sure
we remember who it was.
And then when we're done,
we got to release that same guy.
Here's how we do it.
Let's go to the seize block and
you'll see I click on the seize, and
I've got this, it looks like this
complicated bunch of stuff here.
So let's click onto what amounts to add or
edit.
And you'll see that the type
of seize we've done is that
we've seized a set,
the set is called product one.
We seize a quantity of one
in preferred order, and
we save the name of that guy in
an attribute called tech agent index.
I'm gonna go over this again,
cuz it's complicated.
The release looks like this,
same kind of mess up here but
I'm gonna do a release from
the set called Product 1.
I'm gonna release one guy, and
now I'm gonna release a specific member.
Namely, the person whoever it
is stored in Tech Agent Index.
So seize one guy from the set called
Product 1 in the Preferred Order.
One guy from Product 1
in the Preferred Order.
And whoever that is, I'm gonna store in
an attribute called Tech Agent Index.
So if I see Sammy, I'm gonna remember,
Tech Agent Index is gonna remember that
I as a customer have seized Sammy.
So that name is stored in the attribute.
Now I realize that attributes
only store numbers but
let me just assure you that the name Sammy
is associated with a number as well,
which you don't need to know about, okay?
Then when I do the release
sometime later on,
I'm no longer releasing in preferred
order, I'm releasing Sammy,
a Specific Member who's stored
in Tech Agent Index, okay?
So once I've got him once I seized him,
he now becomes a specific
number that I need to release.
So some remarks.
Various seize selection rules
are possible, not just preferred order.
I could seize cyclically and this allows
me to run through the servers and
not tiring any of them out.
I can seize randomly,
i can seize in preferred order,
I can seize specific member,
largest remaining capacity.
Now if I seize like barber, barber
himself, there may be five barbers, and
so I'll seize whatever resource has
the largest number of servers remaining.
So I could seize barber,
I could seize manicurist.
If there were five barbers remaining and
only three manicurists,
I'd seize one of those five barbers.
So this is really general.
I could seize the resource
with the smallest number busy.
There's all sorts of stuff I can do.
And this stuff is gonna be very
useful when we do our call
center example later on.
So now, demo time.
I'm going to do a simple
model with four servers.
And you'll see it's quite easy.
He's a summary of what we did.
How joyful, we introduced sets,
and especially resource sets.
And then I showed how to use these
guys with Seize-Delay-Release.
And next time, I'm gonna describe in
plain English the call center example,
and it's all the range these days.
So we'll see you soon,
it's gonna be a fun next lesson.
[MUSIC]