In this class, I'm finally gonna get smart
by looking at Arena SMARTS files and
Rockwell demos.
Rockwell is the company that owns Arena.
These are hidden gems that you
can find and play around with.
I actually like Playing
around with the SMARTS files,
during the commercials while
I'm watching a TV show.
So these are fun.
[SOUND]
>> All over the word, the word for
great coffee flavor is Nescafé.
>> [MUSIC]
>> Here's the overview, last time,
I looked at that nutty re-entrant Q and
the crazy behavior In this lesson,
I'm gonna look at these little gems,
the SMART files and the Rockwell demos.
And like I said, it makes great
commercial and bedtime reading.
These are very nice little tutorial files
that are organized by subject area and
occasionally help you with difficult
problems that you might not otherwise be
able to get,
using Arena's terrible help menus.
For example,
there's SMARTS files to create customers
with a time-dependent arrival rate that
varies according to some equation.
That's interesting.
And, in fact, there are 100s of
SMARTS files that you can use.
That's why I look at them for fun.
Rockwell also has many
prepared professional demos.
I'm gonna show you one
of each of these things.
To look for these guys,
you have to sniff around a little bit.
On my implementation, if I go to
Libraries, Documents, Rockwell software,
Arena, that's where you'll find it.
It may differ a little
bit on your computer.
And I'll demo a couple of typical
examples, for instance, SMARTS files,
where arrival rates vary
according to expression,
things like this, emergency room,
these are all very nice little demos.
The summary of what we did in this lesson,
very simple,
I looked at several cool Rockwell SMARTS,
and demo files.
And in the next lesson,
I'm gonna look at a very
easy looking, yet extremely
sophisticated manufacturing cell.
And I'll do an allusion to variations,
including transporters and
conveyors for that cell.
That's sort of a more advanced concept,
but it's fun to look at.
So, we'll talk about that next time.
See you then.
[MUSIC]