Now I'm gonna give a description
of a manufacturing system with
an accompanying demo.
This is a very nice little model that
I'm stealing from the Arena book.
Here's the overview.
In the last lesson, I looked at some
very cool SMARTS and Rockwell demos.
In this lesson,
I'm gonna demo a pretty easy-looking,
yet very sophisticated manufacturing cell.
And I'll look at a couple of variations,
say, involving transporters and conveyors.
The idea is that we can introduce
movement and multiple part paths.
Now you may not be interested in movement,
things like that,
in your particular application.
But the fact that I can do multiple
sequences of paths is very interesting and
very nice to generalize.
So we'll see how that works,
here's a description of the general model.
I've got a manufacturing cell
that's got 3 different types of
parts that are being produced.
Each part follows a different path,
or what's called a sequence,
through the system.
Different service times occur to at each
station, depending on the part type and
the place in the visitation sequence.
So for instance, you could have part
type 2's visiting stations 1, 2,
4, 2, 3, in that order.
And each of those stations will
have different service times.
Even the multiple visits to station
2 might have different service times.
Movement requires
the Advanced Transfer template.
So that's another template
that you have to load.
And then you use blocks, like you use
modules like Route, Station, Enter, and
Leave.
You'll see those in the demo.
You'll also see something called
the sequences spreadsheet.
Which keeps track of the set of paths
that the customers can undertake.
What sequence of visitations
do they undergo?
And you'll need Advanced Sets
to handle sets of sequences.
So you can have a set of anything.
It's perfectly okay to
have a set of sequences.
Now there are ways to get around that.
In this particular demo,
you need Advanced Sets.
But you can look at those if you want.
I won't go into detail during the demo,
itself.
And parts can move in a variety of ways.
They can just move by themselves.
Or I can put them on a transporter or
conveyor, lots of ways they can move.
If you move them on transporters or
conveyors,
that will require construction of
transporter and conveyor paths.
But that's something
that can be done easily.
And you'll see what they
look like in the demo.
This is where all the graphics take place,
and this is the code.
It is trivial code once
you get used to it.
So this right here is Route block.
You might have a Leave block or
an Enter block here.
These things are called stations,
sometimes.
So there's lots of different types
of blocks that you could use for
the variations of this problem.
But it's a very,
very easy problem to code up.
Seemingly a complicated problem,
but it's actually easy to code.
So here's a summary of what we just did.
This time, we did demos on a small yet
very sophisticated manufacturing cell
that really has a lot of generalizations.
We also looked at a couple of
variants involving movement.
And in fact,
this ends our module on Arena,
even though I don't really want it to end.
We're still gonna see Arena later on.
And in fact,
we've only scratched the surface of Arena.
There's so
many other things that we can do.
Next time, though, we're gonna start an
entire module on generating Unif(0,1)'s.
Very easy things, but
very, very, very important.
So make sure you get a little break and
come back and see those uniforms.
It'll be well worth it, so see then.
[SOUND]