In this lesson we'll be looking at
how to generate resource failures in
order to conduct maintenance, or
just failures in and of themselves.
Arena is very good at this and
very simple to do this task.
Here's what we'll do.
Last lesson we learned about
the Advanced Process template and
all the cool stuff that's there,
a treasure chest of stuff.
In this lesson, I'm gonna study model
breakdowns and maintenance in a way that's
way more direct than these fake customer
things that we used in the last demo.
And the idea here is that we'll just be
looking at a certain type of schedule,
a failure schedule.
You can cause resource failures
by scheduling breakdown demons,
like we did before, but
it just ain't elegant.
It's perfectly okay, and if you're on
a desert island, that's what you can do.
A better way is to use the Resource and
Failure spreadsheets in
conjunction with each other.
A very simple way to do this,
it takes just less than a minute.
So here's the Resource spreadsheet
on the bottom of the screen.
You'll see in the last column
there's a Failures tab.
I've clicked on one row,
which is gonna correspond to a failure
that we'll call Drill Failure.
But we'll give the recipe for
all this in a minute.
So, the failure name's gonna
be called Drill Failure.
Then, if I happen to go over
to the Failure spreadsheet,
which is in the Advanced Process template,
I'm gonna see Drill Failure is all there,
waiting for me to use it, and
it's this thing called a comp
failure with a count of ten.
I'll just give it away, what that means
is we're gonna have a failure after ten
people have used the drill.
So, this could be like maintenance.
You purposely take the drill down
after ten customers are there,
then you work on it for
exponential 30 downtime.
Let's look at the recipe here.
We go to the Resource spreadsheet
in the Basic Process template.
Click on the Failures column.
Add a Failure Name,
Drill Failure for instance.
Choose the Failure Rule,
which we'll talk about in a minute.
So right now,
the Failure Rule says ignore.
Let's ignore that for a second.
Then, go the Failure Spreadsheet.
You will see the failure name
that you just chose waiting for
you, all happy and ready to go.
That's in the Advanced Process template.
Choose the type of failure, so
it could be a count failure.
Remember, after ten arrivals, ten uses
of the machine, we have a failure.
Or it could be a time failure, so after a
random amount of time you have a failure.
Both are perfectly reasonable.
Then choose a downtime for
repair, could be any expression.
We had exponential on the last page.
Couple remarks.
You can schedule multiple failures by
clicking on multiple rows of the Failures
column in the Resource spreadsheet.
So we just had drill failure, but
we could also click on rows and
we could have a type I failure,
type II failure, scheduled maintenance.
We could make all sorts of failures by
clicking on more and more rows, and
they get scheduled separately.
Now, remember how I told
you to ignore the ignore?
Well, these are different
types of Failure Rules.
Ignore means it's not a killer failure,
in the sense that the failure happens, but
you get to complete service of a current
customer if there's one in the system.
So if you're working on somebody and
you fail, It's not a terrible thing.
You get to keep on working at the guy.
But then, you reduce the repair time.
So in other words, if my repair time is
supposed to be an hour and the failure
occurs and my customer still needs 10
more minutes, I complete working on him.
So I work on him for 10 more minutes and
the repair time goes down to 50 minutes.
It still finishes at the 60 minute or
one hour mark.
So, the ignore means I
reduce my repair time.
On the other hand, a wait means well, I
still complete the service of the current
customer, but I delay the full repair.
So again, if the repair time is an hour
and my current customer needs 10 minutes,
then the repair finishes at the 10
plus 60 equals 70 minute mark, so
I've waited to finish the repair.
The worst thing is preempt.
When the failure occurs, I immediately
stop service of the current customer, but
I complete it after the repair is done.
So, I got a guy in service.
He needs 10 more minutes, but
the failure occurs, breakdown occurs.
So my current customer
stops getting served,
I complete the repair after 60 minutes,
and
then I remember I've got 10 more minutes
to work on the finish of that customer.
So he's outta there after 70 minutes.
So all of these are kinda nice and
very easy to use, obviously.
Here's our summary.
How ironic,
we have literally succeeded in learning
how to implement failures, and it's crazy.
And speaking of crazy,
I'm gonna give a quick intro next time
to the so-called Blocks template.
It just gives us unbelievable
crazy number of things to look at.
But I'll try to be real gentle about it,
cuz we'll only use a few of them for now.
So, really looking forward
to talking about Blocks.
See you a little later.