This lesson has sort of
the interesting name
of Fake Customers as we continue
our little journey through Arena.
Here's our overview.
In the last lesson,
I demo'd a small electronic assembly and
test manufacturing system.
Very nice,
pulled together a bunch of concepts.
In this lesson, I'm gonna talk about
fake customers, which we use for
a number of tricks.
The idea is that these aren't
real customers at all.
Their purpose is just to do some
specialized tasks that Arena might need in
certain circumstances.
Let me give a little game
plan on the next few lessons.
We're gonna cover material for a while
that will lead us to the stimulation of
a call center,
a little bit sexier simulation.
We'll talk about fake customers for now,
just building up some tools
to get to that call center.
Then I'm gonna look at
the Advanced Process template.
We just got done with the Basic Process
template, now we're gonna become advanced.
I'll look at how we can schedule
resource failures and maintenance.
Scheduling sounds funny,
by scheduling it means we model
the random times that failures occur.
We'll then look at the Blocks Template.
Blocks are sort of primitive blocks
originally found in the old Simon
language, but they're very useful for
a number of different tasks.
And we're gonna start to get
a big vocabulary of these things.
I'm not gonna expect you
to memorize them all but
this is just another template
that you can look at.
Then we'll do some material on sets,
which allow us to
define things like different sets of
servers that have unique specialties.
So we'll talk about those in that lesson,
and
then I'll describe the call center,
then we'll demo the call center.
So with that in mind,
I'm gonna go to fake customers.
So you can use these fake customers
to accomplish various tasks
during a simulation.
Like I said, they're not actual
customers that you care about
in terms of waiting times or
use of resources.
They can use resources but
only for certain reasons.
And we don't care that they have to wait,
cuz they're not real, in some sense.
So, Demo Time's gonna explain it all.
Here's what I'll do in the demos.
I'm gonna use fake customers to
calculate normal probabilities.
For instance,
maybe I don't have my book available.
I just have Arena around.
And I don't have real customers,
then I use these fake customers to
somehow calculate normal probabilities.
Show you how to do that.
In the call center example, I'm gonna keep
track of which time period you're in.
So, we'll use fake
customers to do that task.
And we'll show it at
some point in the future.
And then I can also use fake
customers as a breakdown demon,
so the fake customers
will trigger breakdowns.
Now, in fact, in a lesson coming up
there's a direct way to trigger breakdowns
but I'll show you one thing that
you can use fake customers for.
The summary of what we did in this lesson
is that I just introduced this concept of
fake customers.
And I'm alerting you to
the fact that we're gonna be
using this occasionally several
times in upcoming applications.
So when you see the demo, you'll see this.
Next time, I'm gonna be talking about
this Advanced Process template.
Cuz we're really good
at the basic stuff now.
I'll show you how to get it and some of
the good stuff that you can find in it.
So, see you then.
[SOUND]