Hi, everybody, we're gonna demo
this small, electronic assembly and
manufacturing system that we've
been talking about in the lesson.
Notice that we have two
different types of arrivals.
Part As, they show up exponentially
every 5 minutes on average.
I think that's what we had
in the specifications.
The point is they show up 1 at a time.
Part Bs, they show up every 30 minutes,
but they show up 4 at a time.
And you'll see when I run it,
you'll see, I need to also show you.
See, the Entity Type,
which we defined in the Create module for
Part As is called Part A, what a surprise.
And Part Bs are called Part B.
Now the critical assigns that make
the whole thing work are, remember,
I say we have a Sealer Time?
And I'm assigning an attribute called
Sealer Time to the triangular distribution
of your Part A.
It's gonna be Weibull
distribution of your Part B.
I also assign the Arrive Time
as an attribute called TNOW,
which I discussed in the lesson, itself.
For Part Bs, same thing,
except the Sealer Time is Weibull,
which we'll use in the future.
And the arrive time is still TNOW.
Here's the Prep A Process,
Part As go here.
We just do a Seize Delay Release
on Prep A, totally boring.
Same thing with Prep B.
Sealer Process is the only
thing that's interesting here.
And there it is,
I do a Seize Delay Release on the Sealer.
And instead of exponential sealer times,
the expression that we use
is called sealer time.
And that's defined as an attribute
back in these assign blocks.
So if I get over here to the Sealer,
and it wants to know the sealer time,
it says you're a Part A,
I'll use that sealer time.
Or, you're a Part B,
I'll use this sealer time, right.
Then we undergo the inspection,
this is just a 2-way by Chance.
And it goes with 9% chance to the right,
91% chance down, where it's shipped off.
There's a rework here,
more inspections here, and the exit there.
Let's see what the think looks like.
I've purposely slowed this down so
you can see the pretty little marbles.
It's still, yeah,
it's still too fast, really, so
what did we learn how to do last time?
Go to Run > Setup, and
let's see, > Run Speed, and
we'll slow it down a little more.
Amazingly, I'd already slowed it down
beforehand, but let's run it again.
Okay, you can see, there's the red marble.
And one, two, three, and
fourth guy shows up.
Four blue marbles,
there's one being served here.
Three in line,
four more are about to show up.
One, two, three, four,
there are now seven line here.
See, they're showing up in groups of four.
Now there's only six in line
cuz one just got processed.
So you can see this is very,
very nice, straightforward system.
I'm speeding it up now, finally.
And if you run it long enough,
you'll see various colorful lines
forming over here the Sealer Process.
But it's a very straightforward model now.
The only thing I think I'll
do is that I'll show you
what the full run looks like.
So let's hit the go fast button, and
it looks like, this is interesting.
We did 3 replications for 24 hours,
that's what the 3 means here.
Let's look at the results.
What a lovely chance to look
at Crystal Reports, again.
Boy, I'm never gonna tire of
complaining about Crystal Reports.
So maybe we'll have some music that we
can listen to while this is going on.
[MUSIC]
Get your favorite snack out as we wait.
And here we go, so you can see,
we have 3 replications.
And this is the Category Overview, so
what it's showing us is that we'll look at
the values across all the replications.
So you can see that Part As had
to wait 0.46 units on average.
I think we're in hours,
Part Bs, a little bit more.
And the total time in the system,
it's quite nice.
This is the additional
information on work in process.
So you can see, if you go to the reports,
lots of interesting things.
Okay, I'm gonna show one more small demo.
And it looks exactly the same
as the previous one,
except I'm changing my server logic.
And right here,
we have this assigned block that
supposedly contains the Sealer Time.
In fact, I'm not gonna use it.
What I'm gonna do,
let's click into the Sealer.
And there's that logic
that I told you about.
And so you just believe me
that when I run this thing,
Look at it go, we get pretty much
the same type of behavior in the system.
The random numbers are,
The uniforms that the thing uses to
run are evoked in a slightly different
order cuz I changed things around.
But basically, you're getting
the same results from this run,
even though I used logic instead
of the assignments over here.
So very nice, okay, that ends this demo,
and I'll see you in the next lesson.