Here's our demo on re-entrant queues,
very cool.
I'm gonna show you what's going on,
and then we'll run it.
So create customers every once in a while,
they go to server 1, server 2,
server 1, server 2,
server 1, in that order.
So I'm literally, I was very non-original,
seize delay release, server 1, how boring.
Exponential 0.1 service times.
You can refer to the lessons,
to the lesson,
to see what the server
times were in each case.
They're exponential, like 0.1, 0.5,
but you can look at the order.
The only thing that's a little
different is the priority.
And in each case, the first time I
see server 1, it's low priority.
First time I see server 2,
it's high priority.
Second time, I see server 1,
medium priority.
So that's where I'm getting those.
I'm keeping track of
individual queue sizes,
I'm keeping track of overall queue sizes.
Here we go,
this is a very fast demo, ready?
This is scary, here we go.
Now you can see, boring, boring,
boring, some queues are forming here.
You can see the numbers.
And it looks like server 1,
server 2, they've got some queues.
The queues look a little bigger now.
Server 2's all of a sudden
got some big queues.
Now server 1 seems to be
getting some big queues.
That's interesting.
Now looks like it's gone back to server 2,
and what's going on?
Now let's look down here.
You don't have to look at the picture,
just look at the numbers.
We're are getting bizarre, oscillating
queue behavior between server 1 and
server 2.
One goes up, they clear up,
the other one comes down.
This is the result of the careful
selection of the priorities and
the service times.
And we're gonna get oscillating behavior,
and
not only is it oscillating behavior,
it gets worse and worse.
Let me run it faster and we'll see.
So this number peaked out at 40,
60, let's see what this time.
It will get worse and worse.
75 this time.
So what's happening is you're getting this
crazy oscillating behavior because of
the way that we chose the priorities and
the service times, etc.
etc.
It actually died down a little bit here.
If you let this thing run and
run, it gets worse and worse, and
this is extremely interesting behavior,
which you can play around with and
show and amaze your friends.
So that's a quick demo, take a look at
it and we'll see you in the next lesson.