In this lesson we're gonna be
over Crazy Re-entrant Queue
that could drive you insane,
so be careful.
Here's our overview.
Last time I looked at this one
line versus two lines example.
In this lesson I'm going to look
at a much more interesting system,
a so-called re-entrant queue.
Now, what happens here is that
you're gonna re-use servers, and
mess around with priorities, and
mess around with service times.
So I'm re-using servers,
one customer will go from one to another,
then back to the first guy, you can
get some very non-intuitive outcomes.
And you'll see in a second, so
here are re-entrant queues.
Customers go to Server 1, then
the customer will go back to Server 2,
then back to Server 1,
back to 2, back to 1.
So 1, 2, 1, 2, 1, that's sort of
re-entering, that's why we call them that.
They're depicted in Arena as
5 separate process modules
with Seize-Delay-Release trios.
And like we've done many times,
it's okay to seize The same server
in different process modules.
So, even though they look like they are in
physically different places on the screen,
you are still seizing the same server.
So Seize-Delay-Release five times
servers 1, 2, 1, 2, 1 in that order.
Now, this seems like a totally
perfectly boring model.
Let's make it interesting.
All service times are gonna be
exponential, and here are the means.
The first time we go to Server 1,
the mean is 0.1.
The first time we go to Server 2,
the mean is 0.5.
Then 0.1 in server 1, then 0.1 in
server 2, then 0.1 in server 1,
these are actually chosen very carefully.
Here are the priorities.
When the customer goes to server 1 the
first time, he actually has low priority.
So if there's another customer
going to server 1 down the line,
he's gonna have higher priority.
Anyway, when the customer
gets to server 2 for
the first time, he's got high priority.
Then when he goes to server 1 the second
time, he's got medium priority.
So see what's going on?
The service times are changing and
the priorities are changing as
they move from server to server.
So in other words,
on the customer's third visit to Server 1,
he has a high priority,
exponential 0.5 service time.
High priority,
that's the third visit to server 1 with
exponential 0.5 service time.
So it's a complicated little model, in
a sense, simple model, complicated logic.
Here's what it looks like.
Very simple, we'll see this in a minute.
He goes from 1, 2, 1, 2, 1.
We're gonna keep track of
how big the lines are.
And we're gonna keep track of
the total queue in front of Server 1.
So the total queue is gonna be
the queue here plus the queue here plus
the queue here.
So again, even though server 1 is
physically in the same place, we can
pretend that at least for purposes of the
screen, these are separate little lines,
this is the line that forms in front
of sever 1 when you're there for
the first time.
This is a line that forms when
you're there for the second time.
Maybe they're next to each other,
but they're technically treated as
separate lines, and here's what you
get when you add up the two lines.
So, it's demo time, and
we're gonna see some cool behavior.
Here's the summary.
It was just so cool, so very cool.
Words escape me, hard to believe.
Next time, I'm gonna get smart,
finally and literally.
So, see you in the next lesson.
[MUSIC]