[SOUND] In this lesson we'll talk
about the blocks template which is yet
another template.
Here's our overview.
In the last lesson we talked about
this concept of resource failures,
did a nice easy little demo.
And this lesson my objective is
to add to our ever growing bag
of tricks by introducing
this blocks template.
And there are tons and
tons of these things,
these blocks that you'll
see in a little while.
I don't want you to be intimidated.
We'll use a few as examples.
Here is what the template looks like.
Woah, there are lots of blocks.
You can get them from file template
panel attach, sniff around, find it.
Huge number.
Don't be scared!d I'm not gonna
have you memorize all these things,
it's not possible.
If you can look at the names and
kind of put them in the back of your
mind in case you need these sometime.
But they're sort of
a self-contained language,
related to the old version
of Arena called SIMAN.
And they're very specialized in low level,
you use them occasionally.
And they have the ability to be powerful,
but
we won't be concentrating
on them too much.
But we'll use them here and
there in specialized situations.
They are very nice but
we only use a few for right now.
Seize, Delay, Release,
Queue and Alter just for
now, one, two, three, four, five.
So you may have seen again
some of these words.
What?
Well we're seeing Seize, Delay,
Release yet again and why is that?
Why do we constantly see these
things all over the place?
Well, the main reason,
at least in my opinion Arenas
are built in layers over the years.
When they make an improvement,
they add a new template and
sometimes they like stuff so
much it gets repeated.
And so Seize, Delay, Release have
found their way all the way from
the original version SIMAN into Arena and
they appear in several places.
On the other hand for whatever reason
some of these primitive blocks such as
the queue block which we're gonna
see in our first demo example.
You can can't even connect to a Seize
block with a Queue block form the advanced
process template or in a process module
from the basic process template.
If you wanna use a queue block for
whatever reason, you're stuck.
You have to use one of these
primitive seize blocks.
So for that reason alone it's
good to learn these things.
Anyway let's do Demo Time,
I'm gonna show you a couple things.
We'll do a Queue-Seize-Delay-Release
example using only primitive blocks.
And the reason I'm showing you this
thing is that we're gonna see it again
in the call center example coming up.
So I'm gonna blow though
this fairly quickly,
not gonna go into tons of details, so I'm
just gonna show you what it looks like.
And then I'll look at a cute little
example using an Alter block to change
the number of resources
that are available,
the number of servers that are available.
As the queue gets bigger and
bigger, we might wanna
bring in some more people to help us,
and so we use the Alter block for that.
So go take a look at a demo,
then nice one.
As for today's summary,
this time we'll look to that
black template, lot's of stuff.
And later on we're gonna find
some uses for these guys.
Next time we'll look into
what are called sets,
they are resource sets,
other types of sets.
And I wanna show you how these
sets make modeling lots easier in
certain circumstances.
They are really quite intuitive and
they are easy to implement.
So we'll see you next time.
[SOUND]